<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="base-overview"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Base Add-On Overview</title>

  <para>When you download the Spring Roo distribution ZIP, there are actually
  two major logical components in use. The first of these is the
  "<emphasis>Roo core</emphasis>", which provides an environment in which to
  host add-ons and provide services to them. The other component is what we
  call "<emphasis>base add-ons</emphasis>". A base add-on is different from a
  third party add-on only in that it is included in the Roo distribution by
  default and does not require specific installation. In addition, you cannot
  remove a base add-on using normal Roo commands.</para>

  <para>Base add-ons always adopt the package name prefix
  <code>org.springframework.roo.addon</code>, whereas Roo core package names
  always start with <code>org.springframework.roo</code> (but excluding those
  with "<code>addon</code>" as the next package name segment). Every other
  add-on within Roo is considered a third-party add-on. Naturally we try to be
  conservative with changes to Roo core because these may impact existing
  add-ons. Roo core also provides very few commands, and whatever commands it
  provides are generally internal core features (like "<link
  linkend="command-index-poll-status">poll status</link>" or "<link
  linkend="command-index-metadata-for-id">metadata for id</link>") or
  aggregate the features provided by several individual base add-ons (eg
  "<link linkend="command-index-entity">entity</link>
  --testAutomatically").</para>

  <para>Using Roo does not require you to be aware of whether a particular
  component is part of Roo core, a base add-on or a third-party add-on. It's
  just useful for us to formally define these commonly-used terms and explain
  the impact on whether you need to install or uninstall a component or
  not.</para>

  <para>The individual base add-ons provided by Roo provide capabilities in
  the following key functional areas:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Project management (like project creation, dependency management,
      "perform" commands)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>General type management (like creation of types, toString method,
      JavaBean methods)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Persistence (like JPA setup, entities)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Field management (like JSR 303 and field creation with JPA
      compliance)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Dynamic finders (creation of finders without needing to write the
      JPA-QL for them)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>JUnit testing (with integration and mock testing)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Spring MVC (including URL rewriting, JSP services, controller
      management)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Spring Web Flow</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Spring Security</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Selenium testing</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Java Message Service (JMS)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Simple Mail Transfer Service (SMTP)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Log4J configuration</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>We will add dedicated chapters that discuss each of these functional
  areas in subsequent releases of this documentation. In the meantime, please
  refer to <link linkend="welcome">Part I</link> of this guide, our <link
  linkend="intro-exploring-sample">samples</link>, the <link
  linkend="command-index">command reference</link> and <link
  linkend="resources">project resources</link>.</para>
</chapter>
