<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="base-dbre"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Incremental Database Reverse Engineering Add-On</title>

  <para>The incremental database reverse engineering (DBRE) add-on allows you
  to generate an application tier of JPA entities based on the tables in your
  database. DBRE will also incrementally maintain your application tier if you
  add or remove tables and columns.</para>

  <section>
    <title>What are the benefits of Roo's incremental reverse
    engineering?</title>

    <para>Traditional JPA reverse engineering tools are designed to introspect
    a database schema and produce a Java application tier once. Roo's
    incremental database reverse engineering feature differs because it has
    been designed to enable developers to repeatedly re-introspect a database
    schema and update their Java application. For example, consider if a
    column or table has been dropped from the database (or renamed). With Roo
    the re-introspection process would discover this and helpfully report
    errors in the Java tier wherever the now-missing field or entity was
    referenced. In simple terms, incremental database reverse engineering
    ensures Java type safety and easy application maintenance even if the
    database schema is constantly evolving. Just as importantly, Roo's
    incremental reverse engineering is implemented using the same unique
    design philosophy as the rest of Roo. This means very fast application
    delivery, clutter-free .java source files, extensive usability features in
    the shell (such as tab completion and hinting) and so on.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Getting started</title>

    <para>DBRE supports most of the relational databases that can be
    configured for Roo-generated projects such as Oracle, PostgreSQL, and
    MySQL.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
