<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="base-dbre"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Incremental Database Reverse Engineering (DBRE) Add-On</title>

  <para>The incremental database reverse engineering (DBRE) add-on allows you
  to create an application tier of JPA 2.0 entities based on the tables in
  your database. DBRE will also incrementally maintain your application tier
  if you add or remove tables and columns.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
      <title>What are the benefits of Roo's incremental reverse
      engineering?</title>

      <para>Traditional JPA reverse engineering tools are designed to
      introspect a database schema and produce a Java application tier once.
      Roo's incremental database reverse engineering feature differs because
      it has been designed to enable developers to repeatedly re-introspect a
      database schema and update their Java application. For example, consider
      if a column or table has been dropped from the database (or renamed).
      With Roo the re-introspection process would discover this and helpfully
      report errors in the Java tier wherever the now-missing field or entity
      was referenced. In simple terms, incremental database reverse
      engineering ensures Java type safety and easy application maintenance
      even if the database schema is constantly evolving. Just as importantly,
      Roo's incremental reverse engineering is implemented using the same
      unique design philosophy as the rest of Roo. This means very fast
      application delivery, clutter-free .java source files, extensive
      usability features in the shell (such as tab completion and hinting) and
      so on.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>How does DBRE work?</title>

      <section>
        <title>Obtaining database metadata</title>

        <para>The DBRE commands (see <xref linkend="dbre_commands" /> below)
        make live connections to the database configured in your Roo project
        and obtain database metadata from the JDBC driver's implementation of
        the standard <link
        xlink:href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/java/sql/DatabaseMetaData.html">java.sql.DatabaseMetadata</link>
        interface. When the database is reverse engineered, the metadata
        information is converted to XML and is stored and maintained in the
        .roo-dbre file in the root directory of your project. DBRE creates JPA
        entities based on the table names in your database and fields based on
        the column names in the tables. Simple and composite primary keys are
        supported (see <xref linkend="dbre_composite_keys" /> for more
        details) and relationships between entities are also created using the
        imported and exported key information obtained from the
        metadata.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Class and field name creation</title>

        <para>DBRE creates entity classes with names that are derived from the
        associated table name using a simple algorithm. If a table's name
        contains an underscore, hyphen, forward or back slash character, an
        upper case letter is substituted for each of these characters. This is
        also similar for column and field names. The following tables contain
        some examples.</para>

        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center">Table name</entry>

                <entry align="center">DBRE-produced entity class name</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>order</entry>

                <entry>Order.java</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>line_item</entry>

                <entry>LineItem.java</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>EAM_MEASUREMENT_DATA_1H</entry>

                <entry>EamMeasurementData1h.java</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>COM-FOO\BAR</entry>

                <entry>ComFooBar.java</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>

        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center">Column name</entry>

                <entry align="center">DBRE-produced field name</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>order</entry>

                <entry>order</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>EMPLOYEE_NUMBER</entry>

                <entry>employeeNumber</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>USR_CNT</entry>

                <entry>usrCnt</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="dbre_installation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>DBRE supports most of the relational databases that can be
    configured for Roo-managed projects such as <link
    xlink:href="http://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</link>, <link
    xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/sqlserver">MS SQL</link>, and <link
    xlink:href="http://www.postgresql.org/">PostgreSQL</link>. These drivers
    are auto-detected by Roo and you will be prompted by the Roo shell to
    download your configured database's JDBC driver when you first issue the
    database introspect or database reverse engineer commands (see <xref
    linkend="dbre_commands" /> below). For example, if you have configured
    your Roo project to use a MySQL database, when the database introspect
    command is first issued, you will see the following console output:</para>

    <para><programlisting>roo&gt; database introspect --schema no-schema-required 
Located add-on that may offer this JDBC driver
1 found, sorted by rank; T = trusted developer; R = Roo 1.1 compatible
ID T R DESCRIPTION -------------------------------------------------------------
01 Y Y 5.1.13.0001 #jdbcdriver driverclass:com.mysql.jdbc.Driver. This...
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------
[HINT] use 'addon info id --searchResultId ..' to see details about a search result
[HINT] use 'addon install id --searchResultId ..' to install a specific search result, or
[HINT] use 'addon install bundle --bundleSymbolicName TAB' to install a specific add-on version
JDBC driver not available for 'com.mysql.jdbc.Driver'</programlisting></para>

    <para>You can get further information about the search result with the
    following command:<programlisting>roo&gt; addon info id --searchResultId 01</programlisting></para>

    <para>This may list several versions of a driver if available.</para>

    <para>You can then install the latest MySQL JDBC driver by entering the
    following Roo command:</para>

    <para><programlisting>roo&gt; addon install id --searchResultId 01</programlisting></para>

    <para>Alternatively, to install a different version (if available) of the
    driver you can use the following command:<programlisting>roo&gt; addon install bundle --bundleSymbolicName org.springframework.roo.wrapping.mysql-connector-java;&lt;version&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>The JDBC driver for MySQL is immediately available for you to use.
    You can now enter the database introspect and database reverse engineer
    commands (see <xref linkend="dbre_commands" /> below).</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: currently there are no
    open-source JDBC drivers for Oracle or DB2 and Roo does not provide OSGi
    drivers for these databases. If you are an Oracle or DB2 user, you will
    need to obtain an OSGi-enabled driver from Oracle or IBM respectively or
    wrap your own Oracle or DB2 driver jars using Roo's wrapping facility. Use
    the <link linkend="command-index-addon-create-wrapper">addon create
    wrapper</link> to turn an existing DB2 or Oracle JDBC driver into an OSGi
    bundle you can install into Roo.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title xml:id="dbre_commands">DBRE Add-On commands</title>

    <para>After you have configured your persistence layer with the <link
    linkend="command-index-persistence-setup">persistence setup</link> command
    and installed all the JDBC drivers, you can introspect and reverse
    engineer the database configured for your project. DBRE contains two
    commands:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">database introspect --schema</emphasis> --file --enableViews</programlisting></para>

        <para>This command displays the database structure, or schema, in XML
        format. The --schema is mandatory and for databases which support
        schemas, you can press tab to display a list of schemas from your
        database. You can use the --file option to save the information to the
        specified file.</para>

        <para>The --enableViews option when specified will also retrieve
        database views and display them with the table information.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: the term "schema" is not
        used by all databases, such as MySQL and Firebird, and for these
        databases the target database name is contained in the JDBC URL
        connection string. However the --schema option is still required but
        Roo's tab assist feature will display "no-schema-required".</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">database reverse engineer --schema</emphasis> --package --testAutomatically --enableViews --includeTables --excludeTables</programlisting></para>

        <para>This command creates JPA entities in your project representing
        the tables and columns in your database. As for the database
        introspect command, the --schema option is required and tab assistance
        is available. You can use the --package option to specify a Java
        package where your entities will be created. If you do not specify the
        --package option on second and subsequent executions of the database
        reverse engineer command, new entities will be created in the same
        package as they were previously created in.</para>

        <para>Use the --testAutomatically option to create integration tests
        automatically for each new entity created by reverse
        engineering.</para>

        <para>The --enableViews option when specified will also retrieve
        database views and reverse engineer them into entities. Note that this
        option should only be used in specialised use cases only, such as
        those with database triggers.</para>

        <para>You can use the --includeTables and --excludeTables option to
        specify tables that you want or do not want reverse engineered
        respectively. The options can take one or more table names. If more
        than one table is required, the tables must be enclosed in double
        quotes and each separated by a space. Wild-card searching is also
        permitted using the asterisk (*) character to match one or more
        characters or the '?' character to match exactly one character. For
        example:</para>

        <para><programlisting>roo&gt; database reverse engineer --schema order --package ~.domain --includeTables "foo* bar?"</programlisting></para>

        <para>This will reverse engineer all tables who table whose name
        starts with 'foo' and any table called bar with one extra character,
        such as 'bar1' or 'bars'.</para>

        <para><programlisting>roo&gt; database reverse engineer --schema order --package ~.domain --excludeTables "foo* bar?"</programlisting></para>

        <para>This will reverse engineer all tables
        <emphasis>except</emphasis> any table whose name starts with 'foo' and
        any table called bar with one extra character, such as 'bar1' or
        'bars'.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: excluding tables not only
        prevent entities from being created but associations are also not
        created in other entities. This is done to prevent compile errors in
        the source code.</para>

        <para>Since the DBRE Add-on provides incremental database reverse
        engineering, you can execute the command as many times as you want and
        your JPA entities will be maintained by Roo, that is, new fields will
        be added if new columns are added to a table, or fields will be
        removed if columns are deleted. Entities are also deleted in certain
        circumstances if their corresponding tables are dropped.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The @RooDbManaged annotation</title>

    <para>The @RooDbManaged annotation is added to all new entities created by
    executing the database reverse engineer command. Other Roo annotations,
    @RooEntity, @RooJavaBean, and @RooToString are also added to the entity
    class. The attribute "automaticallyDelete" is added to the @RooDbManaged
    annotation and is set to "true" so that Roo can delete the entity if the
    associated table has been dropped. However, if "automaticallyDelete" is
    set to "false", or if any annotations, fields, constructors, or methods
    have been added to the entity (i.e in the .java file), or if any of the
    Roo annotations are removed, the entity will not be deleted.</para>

    <para>The presence of the @RooDbmanaged annotation on an entity class
    triggers the creation of an AspectJ inter-type declaration (ITD) ".aj"
    file where fields and their getters and setters are stored matching the
    columns in the table. For example, if an entity called Employee.java is
    created by the database reverse engineer command, a file called
    Employee_Roo_DbManaged.aj is also created and maintained by Roo. All the
    columns of the matching employee table will cause fields to be created in
    the entity's DbManaged ITD. An example of a DBRE-created entity is as
    follows:</para>

    <para><programlisting>@RooJavaBean
@RooToString
@RooDbManaged(automaticallyDelete = true)
@RooEntity(table = "employee", schema = "expenses")
public class Employee {
}</programlisting></para>

    <para>Along with the standard entity, toString, configurable ITDs, a
    DbManaged ITD is created if there are more columns in the employee table
    apart from a primary key column. For example, if the employee table has
    mandatory employee name and employee number columns, and a nullable age
    column the ITD could look like this:</para>

    <para><programlisting>privileged aspect Employee_Roo_DbManaged {
    
    @Column(name = "employee_number")
    @NotNull
    private String Employee.employeeNumber;
    
    public String Employee.getEmployeeNumber() {
        return this.employeeNumber;
    }
    
    public void Employee.setEmployeeNumber(String employeeNumber) {
        this.employeeNumber = employeeNumber;
    }

    @Column(name = "employee_name", length = "100")
    @NotNull
    private String Employee.employeeName;
    
    public String Employee.getEmployeeName() {
        return this.employeeName;
    }
    
    public void Employee.setEmployeeName(String employeeName) {
        this.employeeName = employeeName;
    }

    @Column(name = "age")
    private Integer Employee.age;
    
    public Integer Employee.getAge() {
        return this.age;
    }
    
    public void Employee.setAge(Integer age) {
        this.age = age;
    }

    ...
}</programlisting></para>

    <para>If you do not want DBRE to manage your entity any more, you can
    "push-in" refactor the fields and methods in the DbManaged ITD and remove
    the @RooDbManaged annotation from the .java file.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Supported JPA 2.0 features</title>

    <para>DBRE will produce and maintain primary key fields, including
    composite keys, entity relationships such as many-valued and single-valued
    associations, and other fields annotated with the JPA @Column
    annotation.</para>

    <para>The following sections describe the features currently
    supported.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Simple primary keys</title>

      <para>For a table with a single primary key column, DBRE causes an
      identifier field to be created in the entity ITD annotated with @Id and
      @Column. This is similar to executing the entity command by
      itself.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title xml:id="dbre_composite_keys">Composite primary keys</title>

      <para>For tables with two or more primary key columns, DBRE will create
      a primary key class annotated with @RooIdentifier(dbManaged = true) and
      add the "identifierType" attribute with the identifier class name to the
      @RooEntity annotation in the entity class. For example, a line_item
      table has two primary keys, line_item_id and order_id. DBRE will create
      the LineItem entity class and LineItemPK identifier class as
      follows:</para>

      <para><programlisting>@RooJavaBean
@RooToString
@RooDbManaged(automaticallyDelete = true)
@RooEntity(identifierType = LineItemPK.class, table = "line_item", schema = "order")
public class LineItem {
}</programlisting></para>

      <para><programlisting>@RooIdentifier(dbManaged = true)
public class LineItemPK {
}</programlisting></para>

      <para>Roo will automatically create the entity ITD containing a field
      annotated with @EmbeddedId with type LineItemPK as follows:</para>

      <para><programlisting>privileged aspect LineItem_Roo_Entity {
    
    declare @type: LineItem: @Entity;
    
    declare @type: LineItem: @Table(name = "line_item", schema = "order");
    
    @PersistenceContext
    transient EntityManager LineItem.entityManager;
    
    @EmbeddedId
    private LineItemPK LineItem.id;
    
    public LineItemPK LineItem.getId() {
        return this.id;
    }
    
    public void LineItem.setId(LineItemPK id) {
        this.id = id;
    }

    ...
}</programlisting></para>

      <para>and an identifier ITD for the LineItemPK class containing the
      primary key fields and the type annotation for @Embeddable, as
      follows:</para>

      <para><programlisting>privileged aspect LineItemPK_Roo_Identifier {
    
    declare @type: LineItemPK: @Embeddable;
    
    @Column(name = "line_item_id", nullable = false)
    private BigDecimal LineItemPK.lineItemId;
    
    @Column(name = "order_id", nullable = false)
    private BigDecimal LineItemPK.orderId;
    
    public LineItemPK.new(BigDecimal lineItemId, BigDecimal orderId) {
        super();
        this.lineItemId = lineItemId;
        this.orderId = orderId;
    }

    private LineItemPK.new() {
        super();
    }

    ...
}</programlisting></para>

      <para>If you decide that your table does not require a composite primary
      key anymore, the next time you execute the database reverse engineer
      command, Roo will automatically change the entity to use a single
      primary key and remove the identifier class if it is permitted.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Entity relationships</title>

      <para>One of the powerful features of DBRE is its ability to create
      relationships between entities automatically based on the foreign key
      information in the .roo-dbre XML file. The following sections describe
      the associations that can be created.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Many-valued associations with many-to-many multiplicity</title>

        <para>Many-to-many associations are created if a join table is
        detected by DBRE. To be identified as a many-to-many join table, the
        table must have exactly two primary keys and have exactly two
        foreign-keys pointing to other entity tables and have no other
        columns.</para>

        <para>For example, the database contains a product table and a
        supplier table. The database has been modelled such that a product can
        have many suppliers and a supplier can have many products. A join
        table called product_supplier also exists and links the two tables
        together by having a composite primary key made up of the product id
        and supplier id and foreign keys pointing to each of the primary keys
        of the product and supplier tables. DBRE will create a bi-directional
        many-to-many association. DBRE will designate which entities are the
        owning and inverse sides of the association respectively and annotate
        the fields accordingly as shown in the following code snippets:</para>

        <para><programlisting>privileged aspect Product_Roo_DbManaged {
    
    @ManyToMany
    @JoinTable(name = "product_supplier", 
        joinColumns = { 
            @JoinColumn(name = "prod_id") }, 
        inverseJoinColumns = { 
            @JoinColumn(name = "supp_id") })
    private Set&lt;Supplier&gt; Product.suppliers;

    ...
}</programlisting> <programlisting>privileged aspect Supplier_Roo_DbManaged {
    
    @ManyToMany(mappedBy = "suppliers")
    private Set&lt;Product&gt; Supplier.products;

    ...
}</programlisting></para>

        <para>DBRE will also create many-to-many associations where the two
        tables each have composite primary keys. For example:</para>

        <para><programlisting>privileged aspect Foo_Roo_DbManaged {

    @ManyToMany
    @JoinTable(name = "foo_bar", 
        joinColumns = { 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_bar_id1", referencedColumnName = "foo_id1"), 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_bar_id2", referencedColumnName = "foo_id2") }, 
        inverseJoinColumns = { 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_bar_id1", referencedColumnName = "bar_id1"), 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_bar_id2", referencedColumnName = "bar_id2") })
    private Set&lt;Bar&gt; Foo.bars;

    ...
}</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Single-valued associations to other entities that have
        one-to-one multiplicity</title>

        <para>If the foreign key column represents the entire primary key (or
        the entire index) then the relationship between the tables will be one
        to one and a bi-directional one-to-one association is created.</para>

        <para>For example, the database contains a customer table and an
        address table and a customer can only have one address. The following
        code snippets show the one-to-one mappings:</para>

        <para><programlisting>privileged aspect Address_Roo_DbManaged {
    
    @OneToOne
    @JoinColumn(name = "address_id")
    private Party Address.customer;

    ...
}</programlisting> <programlisting>privileged aspect Customer_Roo_DbManaged {
    
    @OneToOne(mappedBy = "customer") 
    private Address Party.address;

    ...
}</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Many-valued associations with one-to-many multiplicity</title>

        <para>If the foreign key column is part of the primary key (or part of
        an index) then the relationship between the tables will be one to
        many. An example is shown below:</para>

        <para><programlisting>privileged aspect Order_Roo_DbManaged {
    
    @OneToMany(mappedBy = "order")
    private Set&lt;LineItem&gt; Order.lineItems;

    ...
}</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Single-valued associations to other entities that have
        many-to-one multiplicity</title>

        <para>When a one-to-many association is created, for example a set of
        LineItem entities in the Order entity in the example above, DBRE will
        also create a corresponding many-to-one association in the LineItem
        entity, as follows:</para>

        <para><programlisting>privileged aspect LineItem_Roo_DbManaged {
    
    @ManyToOne
    @JoinColumn(name = "order_id", referencedColumnName = "order_id")
    private Order LineItem.order;
    
    ...
}</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Multiple associations in the same entity</title>

        <para>DBRE will ensure field names are not duplicated. For example, if
        an entity has more than one association to another entity, the field
        names will be created with unique names. The following code snippet
        illustrates this:</para>

        <para><programlisting>privileged aspect Foo_Roo_DbManaged {

    @ManyToMany
    @JoinTable(name = "foo_bar", 
        joinColumns = { 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_bar_id1", referencedColumnName = "foo_id1"), 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_bar_id2", referencedColumnName = "foo_id2") }, 
        inverseJoinColumns = { 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_bar_id1", referencedColumnName = "bar_id1"), 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_bar_id2", referencedColumnName = "bar_id2") })
    private Set&lt;Bar&gt; Foo.bars;

    @ManyToMany
    @JoinTable(name = "foo_com", 
        joinColumns = { 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_com_id1", referencedColumnName = "foo_id1"), 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_com_id2", referencedColumnName = "foo_id2") }, 
        inverseJoinColumns = { 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_com_id1", referencedColumnName = "bar_id1"), 
            @JoinColumn(name = "foo_com_id2", referencedColumnName = "bar_id2") })
    private Set&lt;Bar&gt; Foo.bars1;

    ...
}</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Other fields</title>

      <para>DBRE will detect column types from the database metadata and
      create and maintain fields and field annotations appropriately. Strings,
      dates, booleans, numeric fields, CLOBs and BLOBs are all supported by
      DBRE, as well as the JSR 303 @NotNull validation constraint.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Existing fields</title>

      <para>Roo checks the .java file for a field before it creates it in the
      ITD. If you code a field in the entity's .java file, Roo will not create
      the field in the DbManaged ITD if detected in the database metadata. For
      example, if your table has a column called 'name' and you have added a
      field called 'name' to the .java file, Roo will not create this field in
      the ITD when reverse engineered.</para>

      <para>Roo also ensures the entity's identity field is unique. For
      example if the @Id field is called 'id' but you also add a field with
      the same name to the .java file, DBRE will automatically rename the @Id
      field by prefixing it with an underscore character.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>

    <para>This section explains scenarios that may be encountered when using
    the DBRE feature.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Executing the database introspect or
        database reverse engineer commands causes the message 'JDBC driver not
        available for oracle.jdbc.OracleDriver' to be
        displayed</emphasis></para>

        <para>This is due to the Oracle JDBC driver not having been installed.
        The driver must be installed if you have installed Roo for the first
        time. See <xref linkend="dbre_installation" />. This also applies to
        other databases, for example, HSQL and H2.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Executing the database introspect or
        database reverse engineer commands with the Firebird database
        configured causes the message 'Exception in thread "JLine Shell"
        java.lang.NoClassDefFoundError: javax/resource/ResourceException' to
        be displayed</emphasis></para>

        <para>This is due to the Firebird JDBC driver not having been
        installed. The driver must be installed if you have installed Roo for
        the first time. See <xref linkend="dbre_installation" /></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The error message 'Caused by:
        org.hibernate.HibernateException: Missing sequence or table:
        hibernate_sequence' appears when starting Tomcat</emphasis></para>

        <para>When the database reverse engineer command is first run, the
        property determining whether tables are created and dropped which is
        defined in the persistence.xml file is modified to a value that
        prevents new database artifacts from being created. This is done to
        avoid deleting the data in your tables when unit tests are run or a
        web application is started. For example, if you use Hibernate as your
        JPA 2.0 provider the property is called 'hibernate.hbm2ddl.auto' and
        is initially set to 'create' when the project is first created. This
        value causes Hibernate to create tables and sequences and allows you
        to run unit tests and start a web application. However, the property's
        value is changed to 'validate' when the database reverse engineer
        command is executed. Other JPA providers such as EclipseLink and
        OpenJPA have a similar property which are also changed when the
        command is run. If you see this issue when running unit tests or when
        starting your web application after reverse engineering, you may need
        to change the property back to 'create' or 'update'. Check your
        persistence.xml for the property values for other JPA
        providers.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The message 'Unable to maintain
        database-managed entity </emphasis><emphasis role="italic">&lt;entity
        name&gt;</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">because its associated table
        name could not be found' appears in the Roo console during reverse
        engineering</emphasis></para>

        <para>When DBRE first creates an entity it puts in the table name in
        the 'table' attribute of the @RooEntity annotation. This is the only
        mechanism DBRE has for associating an entity with a table. If you
        remove the 'table' attribute, DBRE has no way of determining what the
        entity's corresponding table is and as a result cannot maintain the
        entity's fields and associations.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
