<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="base-gwt" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Google Web Toolkit Add-On</title>

  <para>Google Web Toolkit (GWT) is a technolgy developed by Google to allow
  the use of existing Java knowledge and tools to build high performance,
  desktop-esk web applications. Whilst GWT abstracts away many complexities of
  web application development by not requiring you to learn Javascript and
  HTML nor worry about browser quirks and memory leaks <emphasis
  role="bold">there is still a start-up cost associated with GWT</emphasis>
  and the combination of Roo and GWT doesn’t absolve you completely from
  getting your hands a little dirty. This chapter aims to explain how Roo can
  reduce the time cost involved with getting started with GWT and does not
  attempt to provide a complete guide on GWT or its use. The GWT team has
  written <ulink
  url="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/doc/latest/DevGuide.html">excellent
  documentation</ulink> to help you in understanding and using GWT in your
  project, the GWT documentation is especially useful when it comes to
  customising your application.</para>

  <para>The GWT add-on enables you to create a complete web application for
  your domain model with a single command. Once enabled, the GWT add-on will
  maintain your application to ensure it reflects changes to the domain model.
  Currently the add-on only has a single command, which can be used to setup
  GWT in any Roo project. As such, <link linkend="beginning">Beginning With
  Roo: The Tutorial</link> can be leveraged when starting out with Roo and
  GWT.</para>

  <para>The first iteration of the add-on allowed you to generate a fully
  fledged GWT web application in under a minute via the expenses script (to
  run the expenses script just execute the command <emphasis
  role="bold">script expenses.roo</emphasis> from the Roo shell). The
  resulting application incorporated several hot new features found in GWT
  2.1, these include:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>the new lightweight <ulink
      url="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/doc/latest/DevGuideRequestFactory.html">RequestFactory</ulink>
      infrastructure for client-server communication;</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>the built-in best practice <ulink
      url="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/doc/latest/DevGuideMvpActivitiesAndPlaces.html">MVP</ulink>
      (Model View Presenter) framework;</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>ultra efficient new <ulink
      url="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/doc/latest/DevGuideUiCellWidgets.html">data
      presentation widgets</ulink>; and,</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><ulink
      url="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/doc/latest/DevGuideUiEditors.html">data-binding</ulink>
      support.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>In Roo 1.1.1 we have built upon this by:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>making the add-on more Roo-like, via a faux-ITD model;</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>incorporating all the improvements and fixes found in GWT 2.1.1,
      such as support for inheritance in proxied entities; and,</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>ensuring that user customisation remains intact upon each launch
      of Roo.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>This chapter will outline each of these improvements in more
  detail.</para>

  <para></para>

  <section>
    <title>GWT Add-On Commands</title>

    <para>The GWT add-on has only one command: <emphasis role="bold">gwt
    setup</emphasis>. With this command you can turn an existing Roo project
    it a GWT web application. This command can be run at any time, even if you
    have included your domain model in your Roo project. If your project has a
    domain model, which is currently represented by Roo’s JPA support via the
    entity and related field commands, additional views will be created to
    mirror entities in the domain. (A full run down of how to implement your
    domain model via the Roo shell can be found in <link
    linkend="beginning-step-2">section 2.5</link> of <link
    linkend="beginning">Beginning With Roo: The Tutorial</link>)</para>

    <para>To demostrate the basic structure of the conjured GWT application a
    new Roo project, with a very basic domain model, will be created using the
    following commands:</para>

    <programlisting>project --topLevelPackage com.springsource.roo.zoo

persistence setup --provider HIBERNATE --database HYPERSONIC_IN_MEMORY

enum type --class ~.shared.domain.Species
enum constant --name Fish
enum constant --name Bird
enum constant --name Mammal
enum constant --name Reptile
enum constant --name Amphibian

entity --class ~.server.domain.Animal
field string --fieldName name --notNull
field enum --fieldName species --type ~.shared.domain.Species</programlisting>

    <para></para>

    <para>This will create project with a layout as presented in Figure
    GWT.1.</para>

    <para></para>

    <figure>
      <title dir="lro">Figure GWT.1: Basic Roo project</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="0"
                     fileref="images/gwt/GwtInitialZooProjectLayout.png" width="0"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para></para>

    <para>Upon running the gwt setup command, regardless of the presence of a
    domain model, a number of static scaffold files will be copied into your
    project. Figure GWT.2 displays the new files and directories
    (highlighted).</para>

    <para></para>

    <figure>
      <title>Figure GWT.2: New packages and files created from running “gwt
      setup”</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/gwt/GwtAfterGwtSetupZooProjectLayout.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para></para>

    <para>Most of the interesting stuff happens in the client package so we
    will concentrate on its sub-packages and files. The two sub-packages of
    interest are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>managed</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>this package contains all the files that are maintained by
            Roo. These are files that are created and updated to reflect
            changes in the domain model. The GWT add-on enforces a number of
            rules that mean that the add-on will not touch source. As GWT
            doesn’t currently support AspectJ the standard definition of what
            constitutes source is different than in other add-ons, such as the
            entity add-on. This will be expanded upon in the section ITDs: GWT
            Style below.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>scaffold</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>this package contains static files that provide a framework
            for the other parts of the application. The files in this package
            are never updated or changed, they are copied to the Roo project
            upon running the gwt setup command.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para></para>

    <para>After initial setup all the action occurs in the managed package.
    The managed package is comprised of:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>activity</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>contains all classes that leverage the Activity
            infrastructure which is part of the new MVP framework in GWT.
            These files are changed as new entities are added or removed from
            the domain model.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>request</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>contains all classes that revolve around the use of
            RequestFactory. For each entity in the domain model a *Proxy and
            *Request class is created as highlighted in Figure GWT.3. More
            information can be found on RequestFactory via the GWT
            documentation, a basic synopsis is: a *Proxy class represents a
            server-side entity and a *Request class represents a server-side
            service.</para>

            <para></para>

            <figure>
              <title>Figure GWT.3: *Proxy and *Request classes</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/gwt/GwtProxyRequestClasses.png"></imagedata>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ui</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>contains all the managed view and ui related classes and
            files. When an entity is added to the domain model 8 view sets are
            created (a set generally includes a concrete-abstract type pair
            and a ui.xml file, an example of two file sets appear in Figure
            GWT.4) and a ProxyRenderer class. The file sets are as
            follows:</para>

            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>*DetailsView</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>*EditView</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>*ListEditor</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>*ListView</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>*MobileDetailsView</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>*MobileEditView</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>*MobileListView</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>*SetEditor</para>

                <para></para>

                <figure>
                  <title>Figure GWT.4: *View classes and *.ui.xml
                  files</title>

                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/gwt/GwtViewFiles.png"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Running and Compiling</title>

    <para>A GWT application can be run in two ways it can be run via
    Development Mode or once compiled to JavaScript from a standard
    application server such as Jetty.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Development Mode</emphasis></para>

    <para>Development mode allows you to make changes to your application
    without having to recompile to JavaScript, a time consuming operation, it
    also lets you to debug your application as if it were a standard Java
    application. More can be found on Development Mode via the GWT team’s
    documentation <ulink
    url="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/doc/latest/DevGuideCompilingAndDebugging.html">here</ulink>.
    To run the application in Development Mode from the command line execute
    the Maven goal <emphasis role="bold">mvn gwt:run</emphasis>, this will
    open the Development Mode console where you can launch the application by
    clicking “Launch Default Browser”.</para>

    <para></para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>GWT Development Mode console</screeninfo>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/gwt/GwtDevMode.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>Development Mode requires that you are using a browser that supports
    the Development Mode plug-in, you should be prompted to install the
    plug-in upon first launch of the application if the browser that doesn’t
    currently have the plug-in installed. Alternatively you can check to see
    whether your browser is supported and download the plug-in from <ulink
    url="http://gwt.google.com/missing-plugin/">here</ulink>.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Jetty</emphasis></para>

    <para>To compile the application to JavaScript and run it in Jetty execute
    the Maven goal <emphasis role="bold">mvn jetty:run-exploded</emphasis>
    from the command line. For larger applications compilation can take some
    time, so running the application outside of Development Mode is often not
    practical but can be beneficial when wanting to test the speed and size of
    the compiled application or to run the application in browsers that are
    not currently supported by the Development Mode plug-in.</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Desktop and Mobile Views</title>

    <para>The application created via GWT add-on comes in two flavours:
    Desktop and Mobile. The default view depends on the device accessing the
    application. If you are viewing the application from a desktop browser
    then the following Desktop view would be displayed:</para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Desktop List and Details Views</screeninfo>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/gwt/GwtDesktopView.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para></para>

    <para>If you are viewing the application from a smartphone such as an
    Android device or an iPhone the following Mobile views would be
    displayed:</para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Mobile List and Details Views</screeninfo>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/gwt/GwtMobileViews.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>To force the desktop browser to display the Mobile view instead of
    the Desktop the “m=true” query string needs to be added to the URL used to
    access the application. For example to access the Mobile view from a
    desktop browser whilst using Development Mode the URL would be:</para>

    <para><uri>
    http://127.0.0.1:8888/ApplicationScaffold.html?gwt.codesvr=127.0.0.1:9997&amp;m=true</uri></para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>ITDs: GWT Style</title>

    <para>One of the critical technologies that underpin Roo is AspectJ with
    Roo relying heavily on its inter-type declaration (ITD) features. GWT
    doesn’t currently support ITDs, but will in the future (please vote here
    to register your support), due to this a different approach had to be
    created which mimics how ITDs works albeit with an impact on class
    hierarchy. To achieve the same end as ITDs an abstract-concrete model has
    been introduced in Roo 1.1.1, this replicates how ITDs are used within Roo
    and provides clear separation between Roo and end-user
    modifications.</para>

    <para>To demonstrate the changes a view class that is created, as part of
    running the expenses script, will be examined,
    EmployeedMobileEditView.java. Prior to 1.1.1, only Roo managed source
    files were created, so upon running expenses.roo a singular
    EmployeedMobileEditView.java was created. Any changes that Roo needed to
    make to this file as result of modifying the server-side Employee entity
    would cause user made changes to be overwritten.</para>

    <para>As of Roo 1.1.1 two class files are created for each class that Roo
    may need to manage as a result of changes to entities. In addition to the
    singular EmployeedMobileEditView.java a
    EmployeedMobileEditView_Roo_Gwt.java file is also created from which
    EmployeedMobileEditView extends. All changes that Roo needs to make to
    will occur <emphasis role="bold">ONLY</emphasis> in
    EmployeedMobileEditView_Roo_Gwt and the end-user has the ability to
    leverage the Roo managed code or override it.</para>

    <para>Following Roo convention a managed abstract class from which a
    concrete class extends is suffixed with “_Roo_Gwt”, a warning is also
    placed at the top of the source file. If a class is not referenced by
    another type only a warning is placed at the top of the source file. These
    naming conventions and warnings serve to highlight that this file is
    “owned” by Roo and a user shouldn’t make changes to the file.</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>UiBinder ui.xml Files</title>

    <para>In addition to Roo respecting user modifications to GWT client-side
    types changes made to UiBinder xml files are also preserved. The current
    implementation is fairly basic and round-tripping support will be added in
    a future release.</para>

    <para>The management of ui.xml file works in the following way:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Roo looks for an element that has an “id=boundElementHolder”
        attribute, if a “boundElementHolder” element is not found Roo leaves
        the file.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If a “boundElementHolder” element is found each element
        contained within the “boundElementHolder” element is examined to see
        if there is an element which has an id attribute which corresponds to
        each bound field declared in the bound type. If an element is not
        found it is added based upon what has been specified as part of the
        original scaffolded application.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>To stop the add-on recreating a field just create an
            invisible element with an id attribute equal to the field not be
            displayed. For example if the field “supervisor” wasn’t to be
            displayed the declared element in “boundElementHolder” would need
            to be replaced by &lt;div id=”supervisor”
            style=”display:none”/&gt;. Alternatively a adding “display:none”
            to the standard declared element’s style attribute can just be
            added.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Roo will re-order elements based on the order found in the
    underlying entity.</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Expected GWT Add-On Behaviour</title>

    <para>Prior to Roo 1.1.1 the behaviour of the GWT add-on was largely
    undefined, the following clarifies what can be expected of the add-on in
    Roo 1.1.1.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The add-on will only make changes to the abstract class, never
        the concrete type. NEVER.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Roo managed files are suffixed with _Roo_Gwt and have a warning
        comment in the first line notifying the user should not edit the
        file.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>When a user adds/deletes/edits a field in a monitored Entity the
        addon will make appropriate changes in the mirrored types abstract
        classes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>When an entity is deleted, or the @RooEntity annotation is
        removed, the mirrored types will remain in play as to remain
        consistent with not touch user source.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Roo non-destructively manages a UiBinder xml file, thought
        formatting is lost in the process.</para>

        <para></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Migrating an Roo GWT project (1.1 -&gt; 1.1.1+)</title>

    <para>Unfortunately a number of breaking API changes in GWT happened with
    the release of GWT 2.1.1. Like any application built with an external
    library you will need to refactor your application to deal with these
    changes.</para>

    <para>The transition to the new abstract-concrete model and its associated
    benefits is not an automatic one. To take advantage of the new
    abstract-construct model in GWT add-on you will need to inherit from the
    respective *_Roo_Gwt files and optionally remove the methods in the
    concrete type that have been declared in the *_Roo_Gwt file.</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Known GWT Issues</emphasis></para>

    <para>Whilst a number of issues have been resolved in the GWT 2.1.1 there
    are still two problems you will most likely come across.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>RequestFactory doesn't support is*()/had*() methods for
        primitive booleans and EditorModel doesn't realise that primitive
        types are now supported in Proxies, which means that primitives are
        still not supported in the GWT add-on.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>“mvn clean gwt:compile” doesn’t work and a “mvn clean compile
        gwt:compile” needs to be used.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The “Deprecated use of id="boundElementHolder"” warning will be
        removed when round-tripping support is added.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
