<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="base-cloud-foundry"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Cloud Foundry Add-On</title>

  <para>VMware <link xlink:href="www.cloudfoundry.org">Cloud Foundry</link> is
  a recently-released platform as a service (PaaS) offering for developers on
  many popular programming languages, including Java.</para>

  <para>Spring Roo provides comprehensive integration with Cloud Foundry. With
  Roo you can easily login to Cloud Foundry, view your applications, bind to
  services, deploy applications and gather statistics. In fact there are more
  than 30 unique Cloud Foundry commands added to the Spring Roo shell to help
  you explore and benefit from Cloud Foundry.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Installing the Cloud Foundry Add-On</title>

    <para>The Cloud Foundry add-on provides the mechanism through which Cloud
    Foundry features are available in Spring Roo. To install this add-on, you
    simply load Spring Roo 1.1.3 and type (most of which can be completed
    using the TAB key, or CTRL + SPACE if using STS):</para>

    <programlisting>pgp automatic trust
addon install bundle --bundleSymbolicName org.springframework.roo.addon.cloud.foundry </programlisting>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/cloud-foundry/ManuallyInstallingTheCloudFoundryAddOn.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The “pgp” command simply ensures the signed bundles needed by the
    Cloud Foundry add-on can be installed. The “addon install” command
    instructs Roo to download and install the Cloud Foundry support. The
    add-on is successfully installed once you see the “Successfully installed
    add-on: Spring Roo - Addon - Cloud Foundry [version: a.b.c.d]” message on
    your screen.</para>

    <para>As with all Roo add-ons, you could also install the Cloud Foundry
    add-on by simply attempting to use it. To follow this alternate
    installation path, enter the “pgp automatic trust” command, then “cloud
    foundry” and press enter. A list of matching add-ons will be displayed.
    You’ll probably want to install the first (and currently only match), so
    use the “addon install id --searchResultId 1” command.</para>

    <para>Alternatively you can just executing the following command which
    will prompt you to install the Cloud Foundry add-on, it is still required
    that you enable automatic trust prior to installation.</para>

    <programlisting>pgp automatic trust
cloud foundry login</programlisting>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/cloud-foundry/AutoInstallingTheCloudFoundryAddOn.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <para>The integration of Cloud Foundry into Roo has added a lot of new
    functionality and commands to the Roo shell, in this chapter we will
    explore these new commands and deploy a sample application to the cloud.
    After installing the Cloud Foundry add-on you will first need to login. To
    do this, use the following command:</para>
	</section>
	<section>
    <title>Logging In</title>

    <programlisting>cloud foundry login</programlisting>

    <para>This command takes in three options: email, password, and
    cloudControllerUrl. The cloudControllerUrl is optional, but the when
    logging into Cloud Foundry for the first login the email and password are
    mandatory. You aren't required to enter the email and password everytime
    you login, Roo will store these locally for you. The cloudControllerUrl
    defaults the Cloud service provided by VMware, api.cloudfoundry.com, but
    can be changed to point to private Cloud Foundry instances.</para>

    </section>

	 <section>
    <title>The Commands</title>
    <para>After logging in a many new Cloud Foundry comands will be presented
    to you. You can see these by typing "cloud foundry" in the shell and then
    pressing TAB.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/cloud-foundry/CloudFoundryFromTheRooShell.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

     </section>

	<section>
    <title>Deploying Your Application</title>

    <para>The first command that is likely to be of use is "cloud foundry
    deploy". With this command you are are able to deploy an application to
    Cloud Foundry. The deploy command has a number of options: appName
    (mandatory), path (mandatory), urls, instances, and memory. Roo will
    automatically present you with existing deployed applications to enable
    you to choose a unique name, and will also present any WARs found in the
    project. If a WAR isn't found the "CREATE" option presented. By selecting
    create you will trigger a Maven package, which will create a deployable
    application. Onece the application has been successfully deployed when you
    see "The application 'new-expenses' was successfully pushed".</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/cloud-foundry/CloudFoundryDeploy.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    </section>

    <section>
    <title>Viewing Your Applications</title>

    <para>After running the above command, and assuming that you had created a
    project in the first place your application will be deployed to Cloud
    Foundry. To verify this you can run the command "cloud foundry list apps",
    which will display all applications currently deployed.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/cloud-foundry/CloudFoundryApps.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>


    <para>There are two other application deployed, both of which are started
    and bound to services. You will also notice that a URL has been mapped to
    the each application and that the application that was just deployed
    "new-expenses" is currently stopped and no services have been bound to it.
    The URL has been created and mapped based on the application name, which
    is what Roo defaults to if a URL is not provided.</para>

    </section>

	<section>
    <title>Binding Services</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/cloud-foundry/CloudFoundryListServices.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The next step is to bind the application "new-expenses" to a
    service, before we do this though we need to check that we have a service
    to bind to. To this we use the "cloud foundry list services" command which
    will display a list of possible services we can create instances of and
    currently provisioned services. As can be seen above Cloud Foundry
    currently provides 4 services: Redis, MongoDB, RabbitMQ, and MySQL. There
    is currently one provisioned service, that is an instance of MySQL called
    "misql". As there is already a MySQL service present we are going to bind
    this to our "new-expenses" application.</para>

    <para>To bind "new-expenses" to a service we use the "cloud foundry bind
    service --serviceName misql --appName new-expenses" command. Roo's
    auto-completion makes navigating the options a breeze.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/cloud-foundry/CloudFoundryServiceBinding.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>If you were to run "cloud foundry list apps" at this point you would
    see that the application "new-expenses" is now bound to the MySQL service
    instance "misql". We should now be ready to start the application, but
    before we do lets take a look at how much memory has been assigned to the
    application. To do this we run "cloud foundry view app memory". When we
    first deployed the application no memory value was specified so, as you
    can see below, the default value provisioned is 256 megabytes.</para>

    </section>

	<section>
    <title>Provisioning Memory</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/cloud-foundry/CloudFoundryViewMemory.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <section>
    <title>Starting Your Application</title>
    <para>Now that we have verified that we
    should have enough memory to start we simple run "cloud foundry start app
    --appName new-expenses".</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/cloud-foundry/CloudFoundryStartApp.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>


    <para>To verify that the application has actually started simply navigate
    to the URL you previously mapped to the application, in this case it is
    "new-expenses.cloudfoundry.com", and you should see your
    application.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/cloud-foundry/CloudFoundryNewExpenses.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
	</section>
    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>Cloud Foundry is a ground breaking service and open source platform
    that allows developers to maximise there productivity by not having to
    manage the platform to which they deploy. The initial integration with Roo
    allows developers to deploy and manage their applications with very little
    effort from with in the shell. In this chapter we have installed the Cloud
    Foundry Add-On in Roo which enabled applications to be deployed to and
    managed on Cloud Foundry. We have shown how easy Cloud Foundry makes it
    for the developer to take advantage of the cloud from with Roo, by going
    the deployment process step-by-step. There are other commands that haven't
    been explicity covered by this guide and may be expanded on in the
    future.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
