<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="base-jsf" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>JavaServer Faces (JSF) Add-On</title>

  <para>The JSF add-on allows you to conveniently scaffold JSF managed beans
  and XHTML views for an existing domain model. Currently this domain model is
  derived from the Roo supported JPA integration through the entity jpa and
  related field commands. The following features are included:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Automatic update of JSF managed beans and converters reflecting
      changes in the domain model</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Choice of either Oracle Mojarra or Apache MyFaces JSF 2
      implementations</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Server-side validation based on JSR 303 constraints defined in the
      domain layer</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Integration of <link
      xlink:href="http://primefaces.org/">PrimeFaces</link> JSF Component
      Suite, including automatic scaffolding of PrimeFaces controls such
      as:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>AutoComplete</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Calendar</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>FileUpload</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>InputText</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>InputTextarea</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Media</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SelectManyMenu</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Spinner</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>User-selectable PrimeFaces themes</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section xml:id="jsf-commands">
    <title>JSF commands</title>

    <para>The JSF add-on contains four commands:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">web jsf setup</emphasis> --implementation --library --theme</programlisting></para>

        <para>When this command is run for the first time in a single-module
        project or an empty module, the necessary JSF artifacts are copied to
        the project or module such as the pom dependencies and repositories
        and the web.xml file. A default PrimeFaces theme called "south-street"
        is configured as well in the web.xml.</para>

        <para>The web jsf setup command can be run as many times as you like
        to change the JSF implementation and the theme.</para>

        <para>The --implementation option when specifed allows you to chouse
        either the Oracle Mojarra or Apache MyFaces JSF
        implementations.</para>

        <para>The --library option has only one selectable value, being
        PRIMEFACES.</para>

        <para>The --theme option lets you select one of 30 PrimeFaces themes
        for your UI.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">web jsf all --package</emphasis></programlisting></para>

        <para>The web jsf all command creates JSF managed beans and converters
        for all entities in the specified package. A JSF XHTML page is also
        created in the src/main/webapp/pages directory for each entity.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">web jsf scaffold --class</emphasis> --entity --beanName --includeOnMenu</programlisting></para>

        <para>The web jsf scaffold command lets you create a managed bean for
        a particular entity in your project.</para>

        <para>The --class option is where you specify the name of the managed
        bean class.</para>

        <para>The --entity option lets you specify the entity for the managed
        bean and is only required if the focus is not on the entity you want
        to create the managed bean for.</para>

        <para>If you do not wish the 'create' and 'list' menu selections to
        appear for the entity in the menu on the generated UI, specify false
        in the --includeOnMenu option.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">web jsf media --url</emphasis> --player</programlisting></para>

        <para>The web jsf media command is used for embedding multimedia
        content such as videos and music on your JSF home page.</para>

        <para>The --url option is where you specify the url of the the media
        content, such as a YouTube video.</para>

        <para>The media player used is automaticallly selected based on the
        url or file extension of the media file in the url if applicable,
        however, where this cannot be determined you can use the --player
        option to select a suitable player.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The @RooJsfManagedBean annotation</title>

    <para>The @RooJsfManagedBean annotation is added to all new classes
    created by the web jsf all and web jsf scaffold commands. The annotation
    causes the introduction of the javax.faces.bean.ManagedBean and
    javax.faces.bean.SessionScoped annotations in the *_Roo_ManagedBean.aj
    ITD. Note that if you specify a scope other than @SessionScoped in the
    managed bean .java file, the scope annotation is removed from the ITD. For
    example, if you want your bean to be @RequestScoped, simply annotate your
    managed bean with the @RequestScoped annotation.</para>

    <para>Use the beanName attribute to force the naming of the managed bean
    referred to by other beans and in XHTML pages.</para>

    <para>As mentioned before, the includeOnMenu attribute when set to false
    prevents the 'Create' and 'List all' menu selections for the entity from
    showing in the UI's menu.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The @RooJsfConverter annotation</title>

    <para>When a new managed bean is created, a converter class is also
    created containing the @RooJsfConverter annotation. The JSF converter
    class implements the javax.faces.convert.Converter interface and has
    implementations of the getAsObject and getAsString methods (introduced in
    an ITD) to perform Object-to-String and String-to-Object conversions
    between model data objects and a String representation of those objects
    that is suitable for rendering.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The @RooJsfApplicationBean annotation</title>

    <para>Whenever a managed bean is created for the first time, Roo will
    install a class containing the @RooJsfApplicationBean annotation. The ITD
    generated from this annotation contains the PrimeFaces menu with the
    'Create' and 'List all' operations for each entity. Whenever a managed
    bean is created, provding the @RooJsfManagedBean includeOnMenu attribute
    is either not specifed or set to 'true', new menu selections are
    automatically added to the *__Roo_ApplicationBean.aj ITD. Similarly, when
    a managaed bean is deleted or the includeOnMenu attribute is set to false,
    the menu selections are removed.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The bikeshop example</title>

    <para>The Roo distribution contains a script called bikeshop.roo that
    demonstrates the JSF add-on capability. Please note that the --equals
    attribute should be specified as true on the entity jpa command for all
    entities intended to be scaffolded with JSF. Alternatively, add the
    @RooEquals annotation to existing entities. </para>

    <para>In the Roo shell, type:</para>

    <para><programlisting>roo&gt; script bikeshop.roo</programlisting></para>

    <para>When complete, exit the shell and run Jetty as follows:</para>

    <para><programlisting>mvn jetty:run-exploded</programlisting></para>

    <para>View the application at http://localhost:8080/bikeshop:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/jsf-bikeshop.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
</chapter>
