<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="base-solr"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Apache Solr Add-On</title>

  <para>The <link xlink:href="http://lucene.apache.org/solr/">Apache
  Solr</link> add-on provides integration between the Roo generated domain
  model and the Apache Solr search platform. If you haven't heard of the open
  source Solr system, here's a quick description from the project web
  site:</para>

  <para><quote>Solr is the popular, blazing fast open source enterprise search
  platform from the Apache Lucene project. Its major features include powerful
  full-text search, hit highlighting, faceted search, dynamic clustering,
  database integration, and rich document (e.g., Word, PDF) handling. Solr is
  highly scalable, providing distributed search and index replication, and it
  powers the search and navigation features of many of the world's largest
  internet sites.</quote></para>

  <para><quote>Solr is written in Java and runs as a standalone full-text
  search server within a servlet container such as Tomcat. Solr uses the
  Lucene Java search library at its core for full-text indexing and search,
  and has REST-like HTTP/XML and JSON APIs that make it easy to use from
  virtually any programming language. Solr's powerful external configuration
  allows it to be tailored to almost any type of application without Java
  coding, and it has an extensive plugin architecture when more advanced
  customization is required.</quote></para>

  <section>
    <title>Solr Server Installation</title>

    <para>The addon requires a running instance of the Apache Solr server. To
    install a Solr server just follow these four easy steps:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Download the server: <link
        xlink:href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lucene/solr/">http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lucene/solr/</link></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Unzip (untar) the download: tar xf apache-solr-1.4.0.tgz</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Change into the solr example directory: cd
        apache-solr-1.4.0/example</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Start the Solr server: java -jar start.jar</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Verify Solr is running correctly: <link
        xlink:href="http://localhost:8983/solr/admin/">http://localhost:8983/solr/admin/</link></para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Solr Add-On Commands</title>

    <para>Once the server is running you can setup the Solr integration for
    your project using the following Roo commands:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><programlisting>roo&gt; solr setup</programlisting>This command
        installs the SolrJ driver dependency into the project pom.xml and
        registers your Solr server in application context so it can be
        injected whereever you need it in your project.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><programlisting>~.Person roo&gt; solr add </programlisting>This
        command allows you to mark an individual entity for automatic Solr
        indexing. The @RooSolrSearchable annotation will be added to the
        target entity (Person). Furthermore, the following ITD is
        generated:</para>

        <para><programlisting>privileged aspect Person_Roo_SolrSearch {
    
    @Autowired
    transient SolrServer Person.solrServer;
    
    public static QueryResponse Person.search(String queryString) {
        return search(new SolrQuery("person.solrsummary_t:" + queryString.toLowerCase()));
    }
    
    public static QueryResponse Person.search(SolrQuery query) {
        try {
            QueryResponse rsp = solrServer().query(query);
            return rsp;
        } catch (Exception e) {
            e.printStackTrace();
        }
        return new QueryResponse();
    }
    
    public static void Person.indexPerson(Person person) {
        List&lt;Person&gt; people = new ArrayList&lt;Person&gt;();
        people.add(person);
        indexPeople(people);
    }
    
    public static void Person.indexPeople(Collection&lt;Person&gt; people) {
        List&lt;SolrInputDocument&gt; documents = new ArrayList&lt;SolrInputDocument&gt;();
        for (Person person : people) {
            SolrInputDocument sid = new SolrInputDocument();
            sid.addField("id", "person." + person.getId());
            sid.addField("person.birthday_dt", person.getBirthDay());
            sid.addField("person.id_l", person.getId());
            sid.addField("person.name_s", person.getName());
            //add summary field to allow searching documents for objects of this type
            sid.addField("person.solrsummary_t", new StringBuilder().append(
                          person.getBirthDay()).append(" ").append(
                          person.getId()).append(" ").append(person.getName()));
            documents.add(sid);
        }
        try {
            SolrServer solrServer = solrServer();
            solrServer.add(documents);
            solrServer.commit();
        } catch (Exception e) {
            e.printStackTrace();
        }
    }
    
    public static void Person.deleteIndex(Person person) {
        SolrServer solrServer = solrServer();
        try {
            solrServer.deleteById("person." + person.getId());
            solrServer.commit();
        } catch (Exception e) {
            e.printStackTrace();
        }
    }
    
    @PostUpdate
    @PostPersist
    private void Person.postPersistOrUpdate() {
        indexPerson(this);
    }
    
    @PreRemove
    private void Person.preRemove() {
        deleteIndex(this);
    }
    
    public static final SolrServer Person.solrServer() {
        SolrServer _solrServer = new Person().solrServer;
        if (_solrServer == null) throw new IllegalStateException("Entity manager \ 
                                    has not been injected (is the Spring Aspects JAR \
                                    configured as an AJC/AJDT aspects library?)");
        return _solrServer;
    }
    
}
</programlisting>The ITD introduces two search methods; one for conducting
        simple searches against Solr documents for Person, and another one
        which works with a preconfigured SolrQuery object. The SolrQuery
        object allows you to leverage all functionalities of the Solr search
        server (like faceting, sorting, term highliting, pagination,
        etc).</para>

        <para>The <emphasis>indexPerson</emphasis>(..) and
        <emphasis>indexPeople</emphasis>(..) methods allow you to add new
        person instances or even collections of persons to the Solr index. The
        <emphasis>deleteIndex</emphasis>(..) method allows you to remove a
        person from the Solr index.</para>

        <para>All indexing, and delete operations are executed in s separate
        thread and will therefore not impact the performance of your Web
        application (this is currently achieved through the
        <emphasis>SolrSearchAsyncTaskExecutor.aj</emphasis> aspect).</para>

        <para>Furthermore, to trigger automatic indexing of new person
        instances (or updated person instances) this itd registers the
        <emphasis>postPersistOrUpdate</emphasis>() method which hooks into the
        JPA lifecycle through the JPA @PostUpdate and @PostPersist
        annotations. Similarly, the <emphasis>preRemove</emphasis>() method
        hooks in the JPA lifecylce through the @PreRemove annotation.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><programlisting>roo&gt; solr all</programlisting>This command
        will mark all entities in the project for automatic Solr indexing. The
        generated functionality is the same as shown above.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The @RooSolrSearchable Annotation</title>

    <para>The @RooSolrSearchable annotation allows you to change all method
    names through their respective attributes in the annotation. Marking a
    method name with an empty String will instruct the Roo Solr add-on to not
    generate that method (i.e. @RooSolrSearchable(preRemoveMethod="")).</para>

    <para>By default all fields in a domain entity are indexed as dynamic
    fields (defined in the default schema.xml which Solr ships with). The
    default format of a field name is as follows:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;simple-entity-name&gt;.&lt;field-name&gt;_&lt;field-type&gt;
person.birthday_dt</programlisting></para>

    <para>This ensures each field is uniquely mapped across your domain model
    by prepending the entity name followed by the field name and field type
    (which is used to trigger the dynamic field mapping). You can change field
    names by adding a @Field annotation to a field in the domain object (i.e.
    Person) which contains your own field (you need to provide a field
    definition in the Solr schema for it as well):</para>

    <para><programlisting><emphasis role="bold">@Field</emphasis>("my:field:name:birthday")
@Temporal(TemporalType.TIMESTAMP)
@DateTimeFormat(style = "M-")
private Date birthDay;
</programlisting>To index existing DB entity tables each entity exposes a
    convenience method (example for Person entity):</para>

    <para><programlisting>Person.indexPeople(Person.findAllPeople()); </programlisting>The
    URL of the solr server location can be changed in the project
    src/main/resources/META-INF/spring/solr.properties config file.</para>

    <para>Front-end (controller and MVC/JSP views) are currently a
    work-in-progress. However, the following Ajax Library offers a neat
    front-end for those who want to take this a step further: <link
    xlink:href="http://github.com/evolvingweb/ajax-solr">http://github.com/evolvingweb/ajax-solr</link>
    It is planned to provide a out of the box integration with the Ajax-Solr
    front-end through this addon in the medium term.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
