<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="beginning"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Beginning With Roo: The Tutorial</title>

  <para>In this chapter we'll build an app step-by-step together in a
  relatively fast manner so that you can see how to typically use Roo in a
  normal project. We'll leave detailed features and side-steps to other
  sections of this manual.</para>

  <section xml:id="beginning-what-you-will-learn">
    <title>What You'll Learn</title>

    <para>In this tutorial you will learn to create a complete Web application
    from scratch using Roo. The application we are going to develop will
    demonstrate many of the core features offered by Roo. In particular you
    will learn how to use the Roo shell for:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>project creation</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>creation and development of domain objects (JPA entities)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>adding fields of different types to the domain objects</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>creating relationships between domain objects</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>automatic creation of integration tests</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>creating workspace artifacts to import the project into your
        IDE</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>automatic scaffolding of a Web tier</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>running the application in a Web container</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>controlling and securing access to different views in the
        application</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>customizing the look and feel of the Web UI for our business
        domain</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>creating and running Selenium tests</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>deployment and backup of your application</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beginning-wedding-tutorial">
    <title>Alternative Tutorial: The Wedding RSVP Application</title>

    <para>In addition to the tutorial in this chapter, we've published a
    separate step-by-step tutorial in the form of a blog entry. This blog
    entry covers the process of building a wedding RSVP application. It is
    kept updated to reflect the current major version of Roo, and features a
    number of interesting Roo capabilities:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Standard MVC web application with JPA entities etc</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Spring Security usage, including login page customisation</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Sending emails via SMTP</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Testing both via JUnit and Selenium</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Usage with Eclipse</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Creating a WAR for deployment</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>You can find the wedding tutorial at <link
    xlink:href="http://blog.springsource.com/2009/05/27/roo-part-2/">http://blog.springsource.com/2009/05/27/roo-part-2/</link>.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beginning-tutorial-application-use-cases">
    <title>Tutorial Application Details</title>

    <para>To demonstrate the development of an application using Spring Roo we
    will create a Web site for a Pizza Shop. The requirements for the Roo
    Pizza Shop application include the ability to create new Pizza types by
    the staff of the Roo Pizza Shop. A pizza is composed of a base and one or
    more toppings. Furthermore, the shop owner would like to allow online
    orders of Pizzas by his customers for delivery.</para>

    <para>After this short discussion with the Pizza Shop owner, we have
    created a simple class diagram for the initial domain model:</para>

    <para></para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/pizza.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>While this class diagram represents a simplified model of the
    problem domain for the pizza shop problem domain, it is a good starting
    point for the project at hand in order to deliver a first prototype of the
    application to the Pizza Shop owner. Later tutorials will expand this
    domain model to demonstrate more advanced features of Spring Roo.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beginning-step-1">
    <title>Step 1: Starting a Typical Project</title>

    <para>Now that we have spoken with our client (the Pizza Shop owner) to
    gather the first ideas and requirements for the project we can get started
    with the development of the project. After <link
    linkend="intro-installation">installing</link> a JDK, <link
    linkend="intro">Spring Roo</link> and Maven, we create a new directory for
    our project:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&gt; mkdir pizza
&gt; cd pizza
pizza&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>Next, we start Spring Roo and type <emphasis role="bold">'<link
    linkend="command-index-hint-commands">hint</link>'</emphasis> to obtain
    context-sensitive guidance from the Roo shell:<programlisting>pizza&gt; <emphasis
          role="bold">roo</emphasis>
    ____  ____  ____  
   / __ \/ __ \/ __ \ 
  / /_/ / / / / / / / 
 / _, _/ /_/ / /_/ /  
/_/ |_|\____/\____/    1.0.0.RELEASE [rev XXX]


Welcome to Spring Roo. For assistance press TAB or type "hint" then hit ENTER.
roo&gt;
roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">hint</emphasis>
Welcome to Roo! We hope you enjoy your stay!

Before you can use many features of Roo, you need to start a new project.

To do this, type 'project' (without the quotes) and then hit TAB.

Enter a --topLevelPackage like 'com.mycompany.projectname' (no quotes).
When you've finished completing your --topLevelPackage, press ENTER.
Your new project will then be created in the current working directory.

Note that Roo frequently allows the use of TAB, so press TAB regularly.
Once your project is created, type 'hint' and ENTER for the next suggestion.
You're also welcome to visit http://forum.springframework.org for Roo help.
roo&gt; 
</programlisting>There are quite a few usability features within the Roo
    shell. After typing<emphasis role="bold"> <link
    linkend="command-index-hint-commands">hint</link> </emphasis>you may have
    noticed that this command guides you in a step-by-step style towards the
    completion of your first project. Or if you type<emphasis role="bold">
    <link linkend="command-index-help">help</link></emphasis> you will see a
    list of all commands available to you in the particular context you are
    in. In our case we have not created a new project yet so the help command
    only reveals higher level commands which are available to you at this
    stage. To create an actual project we can use the <emphasis
    role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-project">project</link></emphasis> command:</para>

    <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">project --topLevelPackage com.springsource.roo.pizzashop</emphasis>
Created /Users/sschmidt/Development/workspaces/test9/pom.xml
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA
Created SRC_MAIN_RESOURCES
Created SRC_TEST_JAVA
Created SRC_TEST_RESOURCES
Created SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP
Created SRC_MAIN_RESOURCES/META-INF/spring
Created SRC_MAIN_RESOURCES/META-INF/spring/applicationContext.xml
Created SRC_MAIN_RESOURCES/META-INF/spring/log4j.properties
com.springsource.roo.pizzashop roo&gt; 
</programlisting>When you used the <link
    linkend="command-index-project">project</link> command, Roo created you a
    Maven <code>pom.xml</code> file as well as a Maven-style directory
    structure. The top level package you nominated in this command was then
    used as the <code>&lt;groupId&gt;</code> within the <code>pom.xml</code>.
    When typing later Roo commands, you can use the "<code>~</code>" shortcut
    key to refer to this top-level-package (it is read in by the Roo shell
    from the <code>pom.xml</code> each time you load Roo).</para>

    <para>The following folder structure now exists in your file
    system:</para>

    <para></para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/projectfolders.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>For those familiar with <link
    xlink:href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</link> you will notice that
    this folder structure follows standard Maven conventions by creating
    separate folders for your main project resources and tests. Roo also
    installs a default application context and a log4j configuration for you.
    Finally, the project pom file contains all required dependencies and
    configurations to get started with our Pizza Shop project.</para>

    <para>Once the project structure is created by Roo you can go ahead and
    install a persistence configuration for your application. Roo leverages
    the Java Persistence API (JPA) which provides a convenient abstraction to
    achieve object-relational mapping. JPA takes care of mappings between your
    persistent domain objects (entities) and their underlying database tables.
    To install or change the persistence configuration in your project you can
    use the <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-persistence-setup">persistence
    setup</link></emphasis> command (note: try using the <emphasis
    role="bold">&lt;TAB&gt;</emphasis> as often as you can to auto-complete
    your commands, options and even obtain contextual help):</para>

    <para><programlisting>com.springsource.roo.pizzashop roo&gt; <emphasis
          role="bold">hint</emphasis>
Roo requires the installation of a JPA provider and associated database.

Type 'persistence setup' and then hit TAB three times.
We suggest you type 'H' then TAB to complete "HIBERNATE".
After the --provider, press TAB twice for database choices.
For testing purposes, type (or TAB) HYPERSONIC_IN_MEMORY.
If you press TAB again, you'll see there are no more options.
As such, you're ready to press ENTER to execute the command.

Once JPA is installed, type 'hint' and ENTER for the next suggestion.
com.springsource.roo.pizzashop roo&gt;
com.springsource.roo.pizzashop roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">persistence setup --provider HIBERNATE --database HYPERSONIC_IN_MEMORY</emphasis> 
Created SRC_MAIN_RESOURCES/META-INF/persistence.xml
Created SRC_MAIN_RESOURCES/META-INF/spring/database.properties
Managed SRC_MAIN_RESOURCES/META-INF/spring/applicationContext.xml
Managed ROOT/pom.xml
com.springsource.roo.pizzashop roo&gt; 
</programlisting>So in this case we have installed Hibernate as the
    object-relational mapping (ORM)-provider. Hibernate is one of three ORM
    providers which Roo currently offers. EclipseLink and OpenJPA represent
    the alternative choices. In a similar fashion we have chosen the
    Hypersonic in-memory database as our target database. Hypersonic is a
    convenient database for Roo application development because it relieves
    the developer from having to install and configure a production scale
    database.</para>

    <para>When you are ready to test or install your application in a
    production setting, the <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-persistence-setup">persistence
    setup</link></emphasis> command can be repeated. This allows you to
    nominate a different database, or even ORM. Roo offers TAB completion for
    production databases including Postgres, MySQL, Microsoft SQL Server,
    Oracle, DB2, Sybase, H2, Hypersonic and more. Another important step is to
    edit the <code>SRC_MAIN_RESOURCES/META-INF/persistence.xml</code> file and
    modify your JPA provider's DDL (schema management) configuration setting
    so it preserves the database between restarts of your application. To help
    you with this, Roo automatically lists the valid settings for your JPA
    provider as a comment in that file. Note that by default your JPA provider
    will drop all database tables each time it reloads. As such you'll
    certainly want to change this setting.</para>

    <para>Please note: The Oracle and DB2 JDBC drivers are not available in
    public maven repositories. Roo will install standard dependencies for
    these drivers (if selected) but you may need to adjust the version number
    or package name according to your database version. You can use the
    following maven command to install your driver into your local maven
    repository: <code>mvn install:install-file -DgroupId=com.oracle
    -DartifactId=ojdbc14 -Dversion=10.2.0.2 -Dpackaging=jar
    -Dfile=/path/to/file</code> (example for the Oracle driver)</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beginning-step-2">
    <title>Step 2: Creating Entities and Fields</title>

    <para>Now it is time to create our domain objects and fields which we have
    identified in our class diagram. First, we can use the <emphasis
    role="bold"><link linkend="command-index-entity">entity</link></emphasis>
    command to create the actual domain object. The entity command has a
    number of <link linkend="command-index-entity">optional attributes</link>
    and one required attribute which is <code>--class</code>. In addition to
    the required <code>--class</code> attribute we use the
    <code>--testAutomatically</code> attribute which conveniently creates
    integration tests for a domain object. So let's start with the
    <code>Topping</code> domain object:</para>

    <para><programlisting>com.springsource.roo.pizzashop roo&gt; <emphasis
          role="bold">hint</emphasis>
You can create entities either via Roo or your IDE.
Using the Roo shell is fast and easy, especially thanks to the TAB completion.

Start by typing 'ent' and then hitting TAB twice.
Enter the --name in the form '~.domain.MyEntityClassName'
In Roo, '~' means the --topLevelPackage you specified via 'create project'.

After specify a --name argument, press SPACE then TAB. Note nothing appears.
Because nothing appears, it means you've entered all mandatory arguments.
However, optional arguments do exist for this command (and most others in Roo).
To see the optional arguments, type '--' and then hit TAB. Mostly you won't
need any optional arguments, but let's select the --testAutomatically option
and hit ENTER. You can always use this approach to view optional arguments.

After creating an entity, use 'hint' for the next suggestion.
com.springsource.roo.pizzashop roo&gt;
com.springsource.roo.pizzashop roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">entity --class ~.domain.Topping --testAutomatically  </emphasis>                  
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/Topping.java
Created SRC_TEST_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain
Created SRC_TEST_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/ToppingDataOnDemand.java
Created SRC_TEST_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/ToppingIntegrationTest.java
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/Topping_Roo_Entity.aj
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/Topping_Roo_ToString.aj
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/Topping_Roo_Configurable.aj
Created SRC_TEST_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/ToppingIntegrationTest_Roo_Configurable.aj
Created SRC_TEST_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/ToppingDataOnDemand_Roo_DataOnDemand.aj
Created SRC_TEST_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/ToppingIntegrationTest_Roo_IntegrationTest.aj
Created SRC_TEST_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/ToppingDataOnDemand_Roo_Configurable.aj
</programlisting>You will notice that besides the creation of Java and AspectJ
    sources, the <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-entity">entity</link></emphasis> command in the Roo
    shell takes care of creating the appropriate folder structure in your
    project for the top level package you defined earlier. You will notice
    that we used the '<emphasis role="bold">~</emphasis>' character as a
    placeholder for the project's top level package. While this serves a
    convenience to abbreviate long commands, you can also tab-complete the
    full top level package in the Roo shell.</para>

    <para>As a next step we need to add the 'name' field to our
    <code>Topping</code> domain class. This can be achieved by using the
    <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-field-commands">field</link></emphasis> command as
    follows:</para>

    <para><programlisting>~.domain.Topping roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">hint</emphasis>
You can add fields to your entities using either Roo or your IDE.

To add a new field, type 'field' and then hit TAB. Be sure to select
your entity and provide a legal Java field name. Use TAB to find an entity
name, and '~' to refer to the top level package. Also remember to use TAB
to access each mandatory argument for the command.

Afer completing the mandatory arguments, press SPACE, type '--' and then TAB.
The optional arguments shown reflect official JSR 303 Validation constraints.
Feel free to use an optional argument, or delete '--' and hit ENTER.

If creating multiple fields, use the UP arrow to access command history.

After adding your fields, type 'hint' for the next suggestion.
To learn about setting up many-to-one fields, type 'hint relationships'.
~.domain.Topping roo&gt;
~.domain.Topping roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">field string --fieldName name --notNull --sizeMin 2</emphasis>
Managed SRC_MAIN_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/Topping.java
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/Topping_Roo_JavaBean.aj
Managed SRC_TEST_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/ToppingDataOnDemand_Roo_DataOnDemand.aj
Managed SRC_MAIN_JAVA/com/springsource/roo/pizzashop/domain/Topping_Roo_ToString.aj
</programlisting>As explained in the documentation by typing the <emphasis
    role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-hint-commands">hint</link></emphasis> command you
    can easily add constraints to your fields by using optional attributes
    such as <code>--notNull</code> and <code>--sizeMin 2</code>. These
    attributes result in standards-compliant <link
    xlink:href="http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=303">JSR-303</link>
    annotations which Roo will add to your field definition in your Java
    sources. You will also notice that the Roo shell is aware of the current
    context within which you are using the <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-field-commands">field</link></emphasis> command. It
    knows that you have just created a Topping entity and therefore assumes
    that the field command should be applied to the Topping Java source. Roo's
    current context is visible in the Shell (enclosed by a red rectangle for
    illustration):</para>

    <para></para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/shellcontext.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>If you wish to add the field to a different target type you can
    specify the <code>--class</code> attribute as part of the <emphasis
    role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-field-commands">field</link></emphasis> command
    which then allows you to tab complete to any type in your project.</para>

    <para>As a next step you can create the <code>Base</code> and the
    <code>Pizza</code> domain object in a similar fashion by issuing the
    following commands (shell output omitted):</para>

    <para><programlisting>entity --class ~.domain.Base --testAutomatically 
field string --fieldName name --notNull --sizeMin 2
entity --class ~.domain.Pizza --testAutomatically 
field string --fieldName name --notNull --sizeMin 2
field number --fieldName price --type java.lang.Float </programlisting>After
    adding the name and the price field to the <code>Pizza</code> domain class
    we need to deal with its relationships to <code>Base</code> and
    <code>Topping</code>. Let's start with the m:m (one <code>Pizza</code> can
    have many <code>Toppings</code> and one <code>Topping</code> can be
    applied to many <code>Pizzas</code>) relationship between
    <code>Pizza</code> and <code>Toppings</code>. To create such many-to-many
    relationships Roo offers the <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-field-set">field set</link></emphasis>
    command:</para>

    <para><programlisting>~.domain.Pizza roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">field set --fieldName toppings --type ~.domain.Topping</emphasis></programlisting>As
    you can see it is easy to define this relationship even without knowing
    about the exact JPA annotations needed to create this mapping in our
    <code>Pizza</code> domain entity. In a similar way you can define the m:1
    relationship between the <code>Pizza</code> and <code>Base</code> domain
    entities by using the <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-field-reference">field reference</link></emphasis>
    command:</para>

    <para><programlisting>~.domain.Pizza roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">field reference --fieldName base --type ~.domain.Base</emphasis></programlisting>In
    a similar fashion we can then continue to create the
    <code>PizzaOrder</code> domain object and add its fields by leveraging the
    <emphasis role="bold"><link linkend="command-index-field-date"><link
    linkend="command-index-field-date">field date</link></link></emphasis> and
    <emphasis role="bold"><link linkend="command-index-field-number">field
    number</link></emphasis> commands:</para>

    <para><programlisting>entity --class ~.domain.PizzaOrder --testAutomatically 
field string --fieldName name --notNull --sizeMin 2
field string --fieldName address --sizeMax 30
field number --fieldName total --type java.lang.Float 
field date --fieldName deliveryDate --type java.util.Date
field set --fieldName pizzas --type ~.domain.Pizza
</programlisting></para>

    <para>This concludes this step since the initial version of the domain
    model is now complete.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beginning-step-3">
    <title>Step 3: Integration Tests</title>

    <para>Once you are done with creating the first iteration of your domain
    model you naturally want to see if it works. Luckily we have instructed
    Roo to create integration tests for our domain objects all along. Hint: if
    you have not created any integration tests while developing your domain
    model you can still easily create them using the <link
    linkend="command-index-test-integration"><emphasis role="bold">test
    integration</emphasis></link> command. Once your tests are in place it is
    time to run them using the <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-perform-tests">perform tests</link></emphasis>
    command:</para>

    <para><programlisting>~.domain.PizzaOrder roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">perform tests</emphasis>
...
-------------------------------------------------------
 T E S T S
-------------------------------------------------------
Running com.springsource.roo.pizzashop.domain.PizzaOrderIntegrationTest
Tests run: 9, Failures: 0, Errors: 0, Skipped: 0, Time elapsed: 5.413 sec
Running com.springsource.roo.pizzashop.domain.ToppingIntegrationTest
Tests run: 9, Failures: 0, Errors: 0, Skipped: 0, Time elapsed: 0.148 sec
Running com.springsource.roo.pizzashop.domain.PizzaIntegrationTest
Tests run: 9, Failures: 0, Errors: 0, Skipped: 0, Time elapsed: 0.14 sec
Running com.springsource.roo.pizzashop.domain.BaseIntegrationTest
Tests run: 9, Failures: 0, Errors: 0, Skipped: 0, Time elapsed: 0.097 sec

Results :

Tests run: 36, Failures: 0, Errors: 0, Skipped: 0

[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] BUILD SUCCESSFUL
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] Total time: 17 seconds
[INFO] Finished at: Tue Dec 29 15:58:04 EST 2009
[INFO] Final Memory: 25M/79M
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
</programlisting></para>

    <para>As you can see Roo has issued a Maven command (equivalent to running
    '<code>mvn test</code>' outside the Roo shell) in order to execute the
    integration tests. All tests have passed, Roo has generated 9 integration
    tests per domain object resulting in a total of 36 integration tests for
    all 4 domain objects.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beginning-step-4">
    <title>Step 4: Using Your IDE</title>

    <para>Of course Roo projects can be used in your favorite IDE. We
    recommend the use of <link
    xlink:href="http://www.springsource.com/products/sts">SpringSource Tool
    Suite</link> (STS), which is available at no charge from SpringSource. If
    you're not using SpringSource Tool Suite, please refer to the <link
    linkend="usage-ide">IDE usage</link> section of this reference guide for a
    more detailed discussion of IDE interoperability.</para>

    <para>By default Roo projects do not contain any IDE-specific workspace
    configuration artifacts. This means your IDE won't be able to import your
    Pizza Shop project by default. The Roo shell can help us create
    IDE-specific workspace configuration artifacts by means of the <link
    linkend="command-index-perform-eclipse"><emphasis role="bold">perform
    eclipse</emphasis></link> command. However, you should not use this
    command if you have the m2eclipse plugin installed. If you're an STS user,
    you have the m2eclipse plugin installed and as such you can skip the
    "perform eclipse" command. All people not using STS or m2eclipse should
    use the following command:</para>

    <para><programlisting>~.domain.PizzaOrder roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">perform eclipse</emphasis>
...
[INFO] Preparing eclipse:eclipse
[INFO] [aspectj:compile {execution: default}]
[INFO] [eclipse:eclipse {execution: default-cli}]
[INFO] Adding support for WTP version 2.0.
[INFO] Using Eclipse Workspace: null
[INFO] Adding default classpath container: org.eclipse.jdt.launching.JRE_CONTAINER
[INFO] Wrote settings to /Users/sschmidt/pizza/.settings/org.eclipse.jdt.core.prefs
[INFO] Wrote Eclipse project for "pizzashop" to /Users/sschmidt/pizza.
...

[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] BUILD SUCCESSFUL
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] Total time: 3 seconds
[INFO] Finished at: Tue Dec 29 16:11:38 EST 2009
[INFO] Final Memory: 24M/79M
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
</programlisting>Note, when issuing this command for the first time you can
    expect delays while Maven downloads the dependencies and their sources
    into your local repository. Once this command has completed you are ready
    to import your project into STS by clicking 'File &gt; Import &gt; General
    &gt; Existing Projects into Workspace'. Once your project is imported into
    STS you can take a look at the Java sources. For example you can run the
    included JUnit tests by right clicking the pizzashop project and then
    selecting 'Run As &gt; JUnit Test'.</para>

    <para>If you're using STS or have installed m2eclipse into an
    Eclipse-based IDE, as mentioned earlier you can skip the <link
    linkend="command-index-perform-eclipse"><emphasis role="bold">perform
    eclipse</emphasis></link> command entirely. In this case you simply need
    to select in STS/Eclipse the 'File &gt; Import &gt; General &gt; Maven
    Projects' menu option.</para>

    <para>As detailed in the <link linkend="architecture">Application
    Architecture</link> chapter of this documentation Roo projects leverage
    AspectJ Intertype declarations extensively. This does not, however, affect
    your ability to use code completion features offered by STS. To see code
    completion working in action you can open an existing integration test and
    use the <code>testMarkerMethod()</code> method to test it. For example you
    can open the <code>BaseIntegrationTest.java</code> source file and try it
    out:</para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/codecompletion.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>Note, most of the methods visible in the STS code assist are
    actually not in the Java sources but rather part of the AspectJ ITD and
    are therefore introduced into the Java bytecode at compile time.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beginning-step-5">
    <title>Step 5: Creating A Web Tier</title>

    <para>As a next step we want to scaffold a Web tier for the Pizza Shop
    application. This is accomplished via the <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-controller-commands">controller</link></emphasis>
    command. The most convenient way to generate controllers and all relevant
    Web artifacts is to use the <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-controller-all">controller all</link></emphasis>
    command:</para>

    <para><programlisting>~.domain.PizzaOrder roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">controller all --package ~.web
</emphasis></programlisting>This command will scan the Pizza Shop project for
    any domain entities and scaffold a Spring MVC controller for each entity
    detected. The <code>--package</code> attribute is needed to specify in
    which package the controllers should be installed. This command can be
    issued from your normal Roo shell or from the Roo shell, which ships with
    STS. In order to use the integrated Roo shell within STS you need to right
    click on the pizzashop application and select 'Spring Tools &gt; Open Roo
    Shell'.</para>

    <para>Note, that with the first use of the <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-controller-commands">controller</link></emphasis>
    command the nature of the project changes from a normal Java project
    nature to a Web project nature in STS. The first use of the <emphasis
    role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-controller-commands">controller</link></emphasis>
    command will also add additional dependencies such as Spring MVC, Tiles,
    etc to your project. In order to update the project classpath within STS
    with these new dependencies you can issue 'perform eclipse' again,
    followed by a project refresh in STS.</para>

    <para>All newly added Web artifacts which are needed for the view
    scaffolding can be found under the <code>src/main/webapp</code> folder.
    This folder includes graphics, cascading style sheets, Java Server pages,
    Tiles configurations and more. The purpose of these folders is summarized
    in the <link linkend="customizing-ui">UI customization section</link>. The
    Roo generated Spring MVC controllers follow the REST pattern as much as
    possible by leveraging new features introduced with the release of Spring
    Framework v3. The following URI - Resource mappings are applied in Roo
    generated controllers:</para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/restmappings.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beginning-step-6">
    <title>Step 6: Loading the Web Server</title>

    <para>To deploy your application in a Web container during project
    development you have several options available:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Deploy from your shell / command line (without the need to
          assemble a war archive):</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>run 'mvn tomcat:run' in the root of your project (not
              inside the Roo shell) to deploy to a <link
              xlink:href="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Tomcat</link>
              container</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>run 'mvn jetty:run' in the root of your project (not
              inside the Roo shell) to deploy to a <link
              xlink:href="http://www.eclipse.org/jetty/">Jetty</link>
              container</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Deploy to a integrated Web container configured in STS:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Drag your project to the desired Web container inside the
              STS server view</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Right-click your project and select 'Run As &gt; Run on
              Server' to deploy to the desired Web container</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>After selecting your preferred deployment method you
    should see the Web container starting and the application should be
    available under the following URL <link
    xlink:href="http://localhost:8080/pizzashop">http://localhost:8080/pizzashop</link></para>

    <para></para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/standardui.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Securing the Application</title>

    <para>As discussed with the Pizza Shop owner we need to control access to
    certain views in the Web frontend. Securing access to different views in
    the application is achieved by installing the Spring Security addon via
    the <link linkend="command-index-security-commands"><emphasis
    role="bold">security setup</emphasis></link> command:</para>

    <para><programlisting>~.web roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">security setup</emphasis>
Managed ROOT/pom.xml
Created SRC_MAIN_RESOURCES/META-INF/spring/applicationContext-security.xml
Created SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/views/login.jspx
Managed SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/views/views.xml
Managed SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/web.xml
Managed SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/spring/webmvc-config.xml
</programlisting>Note, the Roo shell will hide the <link
    linkend="command-index-security-commands"><emphasis role="bold">security
    setup</emphasis></link> command until you have created a Web layer. As
    shown above, the <link linkend="command-index-security-commands"><emphasis
    role="bold">security setup</emphasis></link> command manages the project
    <code>pom.xml</code> file. This means additional dependencies have been
    added to the project. To add these dependencies to the STS workspace you
    should run the <link linkend="command-index-perform-eclipse"><emphasis
    role="bold">perform eclipse</emphasis></link> command again followed by a
    project refresh (if you're using STS or m2eclipse, the "perform eclipse"
    command should be skipped as it will automatically detect and handle the
    addition of Spring Security to your project).</para>

    <para>In order to secure the views for the <code>Topping</code>,
    <code>Base, </code>and <code>Pizza</code> resources in the Pizza Shop
    application you need to open the
    <code>applicationContext-security.xml</code> file in the
    <code>src/main/resources/META-INF/spring</code> folder:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;!-- HTTP security configurations --&gt;
&lt;http auto-config="true" use-expressions="true"&gt;
   &lt;form-login login-processing-url="/static/j_spring_security_check" login-page="/login" ↩
                                          authentication-failure-url="/login?login_error=t"/&gt;
   &lt;logout logout-url="/static/j_spring_security_logout"/&gt;
   &lt;!-- Configure these elements to secure URIs in your application --&gt;
   &lt;intercept-url pattern="/<emphasis role="bold">pizzas</emphasis>/**" access="hasRole('ROLE_ADMIN')"/&gt;
   &lt;intercept-url pattern="/<emphasis role="bold">toppings</emphasis>/**" access="hasRole('ROLE_ADMIN')"/&gt;
   &lt;intercept-url pattern="/<emphasis role="bold">base</emphasis>s/**" access="hasRole('ROLE_ADMIN')"/&gt;
   &lt;intercept-url pattern="/resources/**" access="permitAll" /&gt;
   &lt;intercept-url pattern="/static/**" access="permitAll" /&gt;
   &lt;intercept-url pattern="/**" access="permitAll" /&gt;
&lt;/http&gt;</programlisting>As a next step you can use the Spring Security
    JSP tag library to restrict access to the relevant menu items in the
    <code>menu.jspx</code> file:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;div <emphasis role="bold">xmlns:sec="http://www.springframework.org/security/tags"</emphasis> ...&gt;
	  &lt;jsp:output omit-xml-declaration="yes"/&gt;
	  &lt;ul id="roo_menu"&gt;
	  <emphasis role="bold">&lt;sec:authorize ifAllGranted="ROLE_ADMIN"&gt;</emphasis>
      &lt;li id="web_mvc_jsp_topping_category"&gt;
         ...
      &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;/sec:authorize&gt;
   &lt;li id="web_mvc_jsp_pizzaorder_category"&gt;
         ...
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</programlisting>This leaves the pizza order view visible to the
    public. Obviously the delete and the update use case for the pizza order
    view are not desirable. The easiest way to take care of this is to adjust
    the <code>@RooWebScaffold</code> annotation in the
    <code>PizzaOrderController.java</code> source:</para>

    <para><programlisting>@RooWebScaffold(path = "pizzaorder", 
                formBackingObject = PizzaOrder.class, 
                <emphasis role="bold">delete=false</emphasis>, 
                <emphasis role="bold">update=false</emphasis>)</programlisting>This
    will trigger the Roo shell to remove the delete and the update method from
    the <code>PizzaOrderController</code> and also adjust the relevant view
    artifacts.</para>

    <para>With these steps completed you can restart the application and the
    'admin' user can navigate to <link
    xlink:href="http://localhost:8080/pizzashop/login">http://localhost:8080/pizzashop/login</link>
    to authenticate.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title xml:id="customizing-ui">Customizing the Look &amp; Feel of the Web
    UI</title>

    <para>Roo generated Web UIs can be customized in various ways. To find
    your way around the installed Web-tier artifacts take a look at the
    following table:</para>

    <para></para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/webfolders.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>The easiest way to customize the look &amp; feel of the Roo Web UI
    is to change CSS and image resources to suit your needs. The following
    look &amp; feel was created for the specific purpose of the Pizza Shop
    application:</para>

    <para></para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/altui.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>Spring Roo also configures <link
    xlink:href="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/spring-framework-reference/html/mvc.html#mvc-themeresolver">theming
    support offered by Spring framework</link> so you can leverage this
    feature with ease.</para>

    <para>To achieve a higher level of customization you can change the
    default Tiles template (WEB-INF/layouts/default.jspx) and adjust the JSP
    pages (WEB-INF/views/*.jspx). WIth release 1.1 of Spring Roo jspx
    artifacts can now be adjusted by the user while Roo can still make
    adjustments as needed if domain layer changes are detected. See the <link
    linkend="jsp-views">JSP Views</link> section for details.</para>

    <para>Furthermore the Spring Roo 1.1 release introduced a set of JSP tags
    which not only reduce the scaffolded jspx files by 90% but also offer the
    most flexible point for view customization. Roo will install these tags
    into the user project where they can be accessed and customized to meet
    specific requirements of the project. For example it would be fairly easy
    to remove the integrated Spring JS / Dojo artifacts and replace them with
    your JS framework of choice. To make these changes available for
    installation in other projects you can create a <link
    linkend="simple-addons">simple add-on</link> which replaces the default
    tags installed by Roo with your customized tags.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beginning-step-7">
    <title>Selenium Tests</title>

    <para>Roo offers a core addon which can generate <link
    xlink:href="http://seleniumhq.org/">Selenium</link> test scripts for you.
    You can create the Selenium scripts by using the <emphasis
    role="bold"><link linkend="command-index-selenium-commands">selenium
    test</link></emphasis> command. Tests are generated for each controller
    and are integrated in a test suite:</para>

    <para><programlisting>~.web roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">selenium test --controller ~.web.ToppingController</emphasis>
~.web roo&gt; selenium test --controller ~.web.BaseController
~.web roo&gt; selenium test --controller ~.web.PizzaController
~.web roo&gt; selenium test --controller ~.web.PizzaOrderController</programlisting>The
    generated tests are located in the <code>src/main/webapp/selenium</code>
    folder and can be run via the following maven command (executed from
    command line, not the Roo shell):</para>

    <para><programlisting>pizza&gt; <emphasis role="bold">mvn selenium:selenese</emphasis></programlisting></para>

    <para>Running the maven selenium addon will start a new instance of the
    FireFox browser and run tests against the Pizza Shop Web UI by using Roo
    generated seed data.</para>

    <para>Please note that the maven selenium plugin configured in the project
    <code>pom.xml</code> assumes that the <link
    xlink:href="http://www.mozilla.com/en-US/firefox/firefox.html">FireFox</link>
    Web browser is already installed in your environment. Running the maven
    selenium plugin also assumes that your application is already started as
    discussed in step 6. Finally, there are limitations with regards to
    locales used by the application. Please refer to the <link
    linkend="upgrade-known-issues">known issues section</link> for
    details.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beginning-step-8">
    <title>Backups and Deployment</title>

    <para>One other very useful command is the <emphasis role="bold"><link
    linkend="command-index-backup-commands">backup</link></emphasis> command.
    Issuing this command will create you a backup of the current workspace
    with all sources, log files and the script log file (excluding the target
    directory):</para>

    <para><programlisting>~.web roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
Created ROOT/pizzashop_2009-12-30_11:23:37.zip
Backup completed in 516 ms
~.web roo&gt; 
</programlisting>Finally, you may wish to deploy your application to a
    production Web container. For this you can easily create a war archive by
    taking advantage of the <link
    linkend="command-index-perform-package"><emphasis role="bold">perform
    package</emphasis></link> command:</para>

    <para><programlisting>~.web roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">perform package</emphasis>
[INFO] Scanning for projects...
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] Building pizzashop
[INFO]    task-segment: [package]
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
...
[INFO] [war:war {execution: default-war}]
[INFO] Exploding webapp...
[INFO] Assembling webapp pizzashop in /Users/sschmidt/pizza/target/pizzashop-0.1.0-SNAPSHOT
[INFO] Copy webapp webResources to /Users/sschmidt/pizza/target/pizzashop-0.1.0-SNAPSHOT
[INFO] Generating war /Users/sschmidt/pizza/target/pizzashop-0.1.0-SNAPSHOT.war
[INFO] Building war: /Users/sschmidt/pizza/target/pizzashop-0.1.0-SNAPSHOT.war
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] BUILD SUCCESSFUL
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] Total time: 17 seconds
[INFO] Finished at: Wed Dec 30 11:36:40 EST 2009
[INFO] Final Memory: 26M/79M
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
~.web roo&gt; 
</programlisting> This command produces your war file which can then be easily
    copied into your production Web container.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beginning-where-to-next">
    <title>Where To Next</title>

    <para>Congratuations! You've now completed the Roo Pizza Shop tutorial.
    You're now in a good position to try Roo for your own projects. While
    reading the next few chapters of this reference guide will help you
    understand more about how to use Roo, we suggest the following specific
    sections if you'd like to know more about commonly-used Roo
    add-ons:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link linkend="command-index-finder-commands">Dynamic
        Finders</link></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link linkend="command-index-web-flow-commands">Spring Web
        Flow</link> addon</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link linkend="command-index-logging-commands">Logging</link>
        addon</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link linkend="command-index-jms-commands">JMS</link>
        addon</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link linkend="command-index-email-sender-setup">Email</link>
        (SMTP) addon</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
