<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="usage" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Usage and Conventions</title>

  <para>In this chapter we'll introduce how to use the Roo tool itself. We'll
  cover typical conventions you'll experience when using Spring Roo.</para>

  <section xml:id="usage-usability">
    <title>Usability Philosophy</title>

    <para>As mentioned in earlier chapters and is easily experienced by simply
    using Spring Roo for a project, we placed a great deal of emphasis on
    usability during Roo's design. It is our experience that a normal
    enterprise Java developer is able to pass the ten minute test with Roo and
    build a new project without referring to documentation. There are several
    conventions that we use within Roo to ensure a highly usable
    experience:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Numerous <link linkend="usage-shell">shell features</link> which
        ensure the primary Roo-specific user interface is friendly and
        learnable</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Only using popular, <link
        linkend="intro-why-use-it-standard-java">mainstream technologies and
        standards</link> within Roo applications</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Ensuring Roo works with your <link linkend="usage-ide">choice of
        IDE</link> or no IDE at all</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Delivering an <link linkend="architecture">application
        architecture</link> that is easy to understand and avoids
        "magic"</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Making sure Roo works the way a reasonable person would expect
        it to</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Forgiving mistakes</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The last two points are what we're going to discuss in this
    section.</para>

    <para>Making sure Roo works the way you would expect it to is reflected in
    a number of key design decisions that basically boil down to "you can do
    whatever you want, whenever you want, and Roo will automatically work in
    with you". There are obviously limits to how far we can take this, but as
    you use Roo you'll notice a few operational conventions that underpin
    this.</para>

    <para>Let's start by looking at file conventions. Roo will never change a
    <code>.java</code> file in your project unless you explicitly ask it to
    via a shell command. In particular, Roo will not modify a
    <code>.java</code> file just because you apply an annotation. Roo also
    handles .xml files in the same manner. There are only two file types that
    may be created, updated or deleted by Roo in an automatic manner, those
    being <code><link linkend="jsp-views">.jspx</link></code> files and also
    AspectJ files which match the <code>*_Roo_*.aj</code> wildcard.</para>

    <para>In terms of the AspectJ files, Roo operates in a very specific
    manner. A given AspectJ filename indicates the "target type" the members
    will be introduced into and also the add-on which governs the file. Roo
    will only ever permit a given AspectJ file to be preserved if the target
    type exists and the corresponding add-on requests an ITD for that target
    type. Nearly all add-ons will only create an ITD if there is a "trigger
    annotation" on the target type, with the trigger annotation always
    incorporating an @Roo prefix. As such, if you never put any @Roo
    annotation on a given .java file, you can be assured Roo will never create
    any AspectJ ITD for that target type. Refer to the <link
    linkend="usage-file-system">file system conventions</link> section for
    related information.</para>

    <para>You'll also notice when using Roo that it automatically responds to
    changes you make outside Roo. This is achieved by an <link
    linkend="command-index-poll-status">auto-scaling file system
    monitoring</link> mechanism. This basically allows you to create, edit or
    delete any file within your project and if the Roo shell is running it
    will immediately detect your change and take the necessary action in
    response. This is how round-tripping works without you needing to include
    Roo as part of your build system or undertake any crude mass generation
    steps.</para>

    <para>What happens if the Roo shell isn't running? Will there be a problem
    if you forget to load it and make a change? No. When Roo starts up it
    performs a full scan of your full project file system and ensures every
    automatically-managed file that should be created, updated or deleted is
    handled accordingly. This includes a full in-memory rebuild of each file,
    and a comparison with the file on disk to detect changes. This results in
    a lot more robust approach than relying on relatively coarsely-grained
    file system timestamp models. It also explains why if you have a very big
    project it can take a few moments for the Roo shell to startup, as there
    is no alternative but to complete this check for actions that happened
    when Roo wasn't running.</para>

    <para>The automated startup-time scan is also very useful as you upgrade
    to newer versions of Roo. Often a new version of Roo will incorporate
    enhancements to the add-ons that generate files in your project. The
    startup-time scan will therefore automatically deliver improvements to all
    generated files. This is also why you cannot edit files that Roo is
    responsible for managing, because Roo will simply consider your changes as
    some "old format" of the file and rewrite the file in accordance with its
    current add-ons.</para>

    <para>Not being able to edit the generated files may sound restrictive, as
    often you'll want to fine-tune just some part of the file that Roo has
    emitted. In this case you can either write a Roo add-on, or more commonly
    just write the method (or field or constructor etc) directly in your .java
    file. Roo has a convention of detecting if any member it intends to
    introduce already exists in the target type, and if it does Roo will not
    permit the ITD to include that member. In plain English that means if you
    write a method that Roo was writing, Roo will remove the method from its
    generated file automatically and without needing an explicit directive to
    do so. In fact the Roo core infrastructure explicitly detects buggy
    add-ons that are trying to introduce members that an end user has written
    and it will throw an exception to prevent the add-on from doing so.</para>

    <para>This talk of exceptions also lets us cover the related usability
    feature of being forgiving. Every time Roo changes your file system or
    receives a shell command, it is executed within a quasi-transactional
    context that supports rollback. As a result, if anything goes wrong (such
    as you made a mistake when entering a command or an add-on has a problem
    for whatever reason) the file system will automatically rollback to the
    state it was before the change was attempted. The cascading nature of many
    changes (ie you add a field to a <code>.java</code> file and that changes
    an AspectJ ITD and that in turn changes a web <code>.jspx</code> etc) is
    handled in the same unit of work and therefore rolled back as an atomic
    group when required.</para>

    <para>Before leaving this discussion on usability, it's probably worth
    pointing out that although the Roo shell contains <link
    linkend="command-index">numerous commands</link>, you don't need to use
    them. You are perfectly free to perform any change to your file system by
    hand (without the help of the Roo shell). For example, there are commands
    which let you create <code>.java</code> files or add fields to them. You
    can use these commands or you can simply do this within your IDE or text
    editor. Roo's automatic file system monitoring will detect the changes and
    respond accordingly. Just work the way you feel most comfortable - Roo
    will respect it.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="usage-shell">
    <title>Shell Features</title>

    <para>Many people who first look at Roo love the shell. In fact when we
    first showed Roo to an internal audience, one of the developers present
    said tounge-in-cheek, "That could only have come from someone with a deep
    love of the Linux command line!". All jokes aside, the shell is only one
    part of the Roo <link linkend="usage-usability">usability story</link> -
    although it's a very important part. Here are some of the usability
    features that make the shell so nice to work with:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Tab completion</emphasis>: The cornerstone of
          command-line usability is tab assist. Hit TAB (or CTRL+SPACE if
          you're in <link linkend="usage-ide">SpringSource Tool Suite</link>)
          and Roo will show you the applicable options.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Command hiding</emphasis>: Command hiding will
          remove commands which do not make sense given the current context of
          your project. For example, if you're in an empty directory, you can
          type <link linkend="command-index-project">project</link>, hit TAB,
          and see the options for creating a project. But once you've created
          the project, the project command is no longer visible. The same
          applies for most Roo commands. This is nice as it means you only see
          commands which you can actually use right now. Of course, a full
          list of commands applicable to your version of Roo is available in
          the <link linkend="command-index">command index appendix</link> and
          also via <link linkend="command-index-help">help</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Contextual awareness</emphasis>: Roo remembers the
          last Java type you are working with in your current shell session
          and automatically treats it as the argument to a command. You always
          know what Roo considers the current context because the shell prompt
          will indicate this just before it writes <emphasis
          role="bold">roo&gt;</emphasis>. In the command index you might find
          some options which have a default value of '<code>*</code>'. This is
          the marker which indicates "the current context will be used for
          this command option unless you explicitly specify otherwise". You
          change the context by simply working with a different Java type (ie
          specify an operation that involves a different Java type and the
          context will change to that Java type).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Hinting</emphasis>: Not sure what to do next? Just
          use the <link linkend="command-index-hint">hint</link> command. It's
          the perfect lightweight substitute for documentation if you're in a
          hurry!</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Inbuilt help</emphasis>: If you'd like to know all
          the options available for a given command, use the <link
          linkend="command-index-help">help</link> command. It lists every
          option directly within the shell.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Automatic inline help</emphasis>: Of course, it's a
          bit of a pain to have to go to the trouble of typing <link
          linkend="command-index-help">help</link> then hitting enter if
          you're in the middle of typing a command. That's why we offer inline
          help, which is automatically displayed whenever you press TAB. It is
          listed just before the completion options. To save screen space, we
          only list the inline help once for a given command option. So if you
          type <code>project --template TAB TAB TAB</code>, the first time you
          press TAB you'd see the inline help and the completion
          options</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Scripting and script recording</emphasis>: Save your
          Roo commands and play them again later.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>The scripting and script recording features are
    particularly nice, because they let you execute a series of Roo commands
    without typing them in.</para>

    <para>To execute a Roo script, just use the <link
    linkend="command-index-script">script</link> command. When you use the
    script command you'll need to indicate the script to run. We ship a number
    of sample scripts with Roo, as discussed earlier in the <link
    linkend="intro-exploring-sample">Exploring Roo Samples</link>
    section.</para>

    <para>What if you want to create your own scripts? All you need is a text
    editor. The syntax of the script is identical to what you'd type at the
    Roo shell. Both the Roo shell and your scripts can contain inline comments
    using the <code>;</code> and <code>//</code> markers, as well as block
    comments using the <code>/* */</code> syntax.</para>

    <para>A really nice script-related feature of the Roo shell is that it
    will automatically build a script containing the commands you entered.
    This file is named <code>log.roo</code> and exists in your current working
    directory. Here's a quick example of the contents:</para>

    <programlisting>// Spring Roo ENGINEERING BUILD [rev 553:554M] log opened at 2009-12-31 08:10:58
project --topLevelPackage roo.shell.is.neat
// [failed] persistence setup --database DELIBERATE_ERROR --provider HIBERNATE 
persistence setup --database HYPERSONIC_IN_MEMORY --provider HIBERNATE 
quit
// Spring Roo ENGINEERING BUILD [rev 553:554M] log closed at 2009-12-31 08:11:37</programlisting>

    <para>In the recorded script, you can see the version number, session
    start time and session close times are all listed. Also listed is a
    command I typed that was intentionally incorrect, and Roo has turned that
    command into a comment within the script (prefixed with <code>//
    [failed]</code>) so that I can identify it and it will not execute should
    I run the script again later. This is a great way of reviewing what you've
    done with Roo, and sharing the results with others.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="usage-ide">
    <title>IDE Usage</title>

    <para>Despite Roo's really nice shell, in reality most people develop most
    of their application using an IDE or at least text editor. Roo fully
    expects this usage and supports it.</para>

    <para>Before we cover how to use an IDE, it's worth mentioning that you
    don't strictly need one. With Roo you can build an application at the
    command line, although to be honest you'll get more productivity via an
    IDE if it's anything beyond a trivial application. If you would prefer to
    use the command line, you can start a fresh application using the Roo
    shell, edit your <code>.java</code> and other files using any text editor,
    and use the <link linkend="command-index-maven-commands">perform</link>
    commands to compile, test and package your application ready for
    deployment. You can even use <code>mvn tomcat:run</code> to execute a
    servlet container, and Roo add-ons let you deploy straight to a cloud
    environment like Google App Engine. Again, you'll be more productive in an
    IDE, but it's nice to know Roo doesn't force you to use an IDE unless
    you'd like to use one.</para>

    <para>In relation to IDEs, we highly recommend that you use <link
    xlink:href="http://www.springsource.com/products/sts">SpringSource Tool
    Suite</link> (STS). STS is a significantly extended version (and free!) of
    the pervasive Eclipse IDE. From a Roo perspective, STS preintegrates the
    latest <link xlink:href="http://www.eclipse.org/ajdt/">AspectJ Development
    Tools</link> (AJDT) and also offers an inbuilt Roo shell. The inbuilt Roo
    shell means you do not need to run the normal Roo shell if you are using
    STS. You'll also have other neat Roo-IDE integation features, like the
    ability to press CTRL+R (or Apple+R if you're on an Apple) and a popup
    will allow you to type a Roo command from anywhere within the IDE. Another
    nice feature is the shell message hotlinking, which means all shell
    messages emitted by Roo are actually links that you can click to open the
    corresponding file in an Eclipse editor. There are other goodies too, like
    extra commands to deploy to SpringSource tc Server.</para>

    <para>You'll need to use STS 2.5 if you'd like to use Roo 1.1, which at
    the time of writing represents the latest version of both tools. Because
    the release cycle of STS and Roo differ, when you download STS you'll
    generally find it includes a version of Roo that might not be the absolute
    latest. This is not a problem. All you need to do is ensure you're using
    the latest release of STS and then within the IDE select Window &gt;
    Preferences &gt; Spring &gt; Roo Support. Next select "Add..." and find
    the directory which contains the latest Roo release. You probably also
    want to tick the newly-selected Roo release, making it the default for
    your projects when they're imported into STS.</para>

    <para>Naturally Roo works well with standard Eclipse as well. All you need
    to do is ensure you install the latest <link
    xlink:href="http://www.eclipse.org/ajdt/">AspectJ Development Tools</link>
    (AJDT) plugin. This will ensure code assist and incremental compilation
    works well. We also recommend you go into Window &gt; Preferences &gt;
    General &gt; Workspace and switch on the "Refresh automatically" box. That
    way Eclipse will detect changes made to the file system by the
    externally-running Roo shell. It's also recommended to install the
    m2eclipse plugin, which is automatically included if you use STS and is
    particularly suitable for Roo-based projects.</para>

    <para>When using AJDT you may encounter a configuration option enabling
    you to "weave" the JDT. This is on by default in STS, so you're unlikely
    to see the message if using STS. If you are prompted (or locate the
    configuration settings yourself under the Window &gt; Preferences &gt; JDT
    Weaving menu), you should enable weaving. This ensures the Java Editor in
    Eclipse (or STS) gives the best AspectJ-based experience, such as code
    assist etc. You can also verify this setting is active by loading Eclipse
    (or STS) and selecting Window &gt; Preferences &gt; JDT Weaving.</para>

    <para>If you're using m2eclipse, you won't need to use the <link
    linkend="command-index-perform-eclipse">perform eclipse</link> command to
    setup your environment. A simple import of the project using Eclipse's
    File &gt; Import &gt; General &gt; Maven Projects menu option is
    sufficient.</para>

    <para>Irrespective of how you import your project into Eclipse (ie via the
    <link linkend="command-index-perform-eclipse">perform eclipse</link>
    command or via m2eclipse) you should be aware that the project will not be
    a Web Tools Project (WTP) until such time as you install your first web
    controller. This is usually undertaken via the controller all or
    controller scaffold command. If you have already imported your project
    into Eclipse, simply complete the relevant controller command and then
    re-import. The project will then be a WTP and offer the ability to deploy
    to an IDE-embedded web container. If you attempt to start a WTP server and
    receive an error message, try right-clicking the project and selecting
    Maven &gt; Update Project Configuration. This often resolves the
    issue.</para>

    <para>If you're using IntelliJ, we are pleased to report that IntelliJ now
    supports Roo. This follows the completion of ticket <link
    xlink:href="http://youtrack.jetbrains.net/issue/IDEA-26959">IDEA-26959</link>,
    where you can obtain more information about the AspectJ support now
    available in IntelliJ.</para>

    <para>If you're using any IDE other than STS, the recommended operating
    pattern is to load the standalone Roo shell in one operating system window
    and leave it running while you interact with your IDE. There is no formal
    link between the IDE and Roo shell. The only way they "talk" to each other
    is by both monitoring the file system for changes made by the other. This
    happens so quickly that you're unlikely to notice, and indeed internally
    to Roo we have an API that allows the polling-based approach to be
    replaced with a formal notification API should it ever become necessary.
    As discussed in the <link linkend="usage-usability">usability
    section</link>, if you forget to load the Roo shell and start modifying
    your project anyway, all you need to do is load the Roo shell again and it
    will detect any changes it needs to make automatically.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="usage-build-system">
    <title>Build System Usage</title>

    <para>Roo currently supports the use of Apache Maven. This is a common
    build system used in many enteprise applications. We routinely poll our
    community and look at public surveys which consistently show that nearly
    all enterprise development projects use either Maven or Ant, so we believe
    this is a good default for Roo projects. As per the <link
    linkend="intro-installation">installation instructions</link>, you must
    ensure you are using Maven 2.0.9 or above. We do recommend you use Maven
    2.2 for best results, though.</para>

    <para>Roo will create a new <code>pom.xml</code> file whenever you use the
    <link linkend="command-index-project">project</link> command. The POM will
    contain the following Roo-specific considerations:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A reference to the Roo annotations JAR. This JAR exists at
        development time only and has a scope that prevents it from being
        included in resultant WAR files.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A correct configuration of the Maven AspectJ plugin. This
        includes a reference to the Spring Aspects library, which is important
        to Roo-based applications. Spring Aspects is included within Spring
        Framework.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>There are no other Roo changes to the POM. In particular, there is
    no requirement for the POM to include Roo as part of any code generation
    step. Roo is never used in this "bulk generation style".</para>

    <para>If you are interested in ensuring a build includes the latest Roo
    code generation output, you can cause Maven or equivalent build system to
    execute <code>roo quit</code>. The presentation of the quit command line
    option will cause the Roo shell to load, perform its startup-time scan
    (which identifies and completes any required changes to generated files)
    and then exit.</para>

    <para>Those seeking Ant/Ivy instead of Maven support are encouraged to
    vote for issue <link
    xlink:href="https://jira.springsource.org/browse/ROO-91">ROO-91</link>.
    The internals of Roo do not rely on Maven at all. Nonetheless we have
    deferred it until we see sufficient community interest to justify
    maintaining two build system environments.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="usage-file-system">
    <title>File System Conventions</title>

    <para>We have already covered some of Roo's file system conventions in the
    <link linkend="usage-usability">Usability Philosophy</link> section. In
    summary Roo will automatically monitor the file system for changes and
    code generate only those files which match the <code>*_Roo_*.aj</code>
    wildcard. It will also code generate those <link
    linkend="jsp-views">JSPs</link> associated with <link
    linkend="controller-commands">scaffolded MVC controllers</link> that have
    the annotation <code>@RooWebScaffold</code>.</para>

    <para>Roo applications follow the standard Maven-based directory layout.
    We have also placed Spring application context-related files (both
    <code>.xml</code> and <code>.properties</code>) in the recommended
    classpath sub-directory for Spring applications,
    <code>META-INF/spring</code>.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="usage-addons">
    <title>Add-On Installation and Removal</title>

    <para>Roo supports the installation and removal of third-party add-ons.
    Roo 1.1 added significant enhancements to its add-on model, as more
    thoroughly discussed in <link linkend="internals">Part III</link> of this
    manual.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="usage-recommendations">
    <title>Recommended Practices</title>

    <para>Following some simple recommendations will ensure you have the best
    possible experience with Roo:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Don't edit any files that Roo code generates (see the <link
        linkend="usage-usability">Usability Philosophy</link> for
        details).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Before installing any new technology, check if Roo offers a
        setup command and use it if present (this will ensure the seutp
        reflects our recommendations and the expectations of other
        add-ons).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Ensure you leave the Roo shell running when creating, updating
        or deleting files in your project.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Remember you'll still need to write Java code (and JSPs for
        custom controllers). Have the right expectations before you start
        using Roo. It just helps you - it doesn't replace the requirement to
        program.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Check the <link linkend="upgrade-known-issues">Known
        Issues</link> section before upgrading or if you experience any
        problems.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Refer to the <link linkend="resources">Roo Resources</link>
        section for details of how to get assistance with Roo, such as the
        forum and issue tracking database. We're happy to hear from
        you.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="usage-add-ons">
    <title>Managing Roo Add-Ons</title>

    <para><sidebar>
        <title>Modifying PGP Trusts For httppgp:// Scheme Operation</title>

        <para>As detailed in the main text, Roo supports a special protocol
        scheme called <code>httppgp://</code>. This performs a Pretty Good
        Privacy (PGP) detached signature verification before proceeding to
        download the main resource. We use this as a key foundation of our
        add-on security model. Many Roo commands download items from the
        Internet, and anytime a <code>httppgp://</code> scheme is encountered
        a PGP verification will take place.</para>

        <para>One common case is if you are using the <link
        linkend="command-index-addon-install-id">addon install</link> command.
        An example of the error if the PGP detached signature is untrusted is
        shown below:</para>

        <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">addon install</emphasis> --bundleSymbolicName de.saxsys.roo.equals.addon
Download URL 'http://[...]equals.addon-1.2.0.jar' failed
This resource was signed with PGP key ID '0xC3A61B10', 
which is not currently trusted
Use 'pgp key view' to view this key, 'pgp trust' to trust it, 
or 'pgp automatic trust' to trust any keys</programlisting>Essentially you
        need to decide if you trust the PGP key ID or not. There is a <link
        linkend="command-index-pgp-key-view">pgp key view</link> command that
        will help you learn more about a given key ID if you would like to use
        it. You can also view keys at public PGP key servers such as <link
        xlink:href="http://pgp.mit.edu/">http://pgp.mit.edu/</link>. You
        essentially have two options to cause an untrusted httppgp download to
        be performed by Roo:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use the <link linkend="command-index-pgp-trust">pgp
            trust</link> command to trust the PGP key ID shown in the error
            message. This will permanently trust the key ID, and it will show
            up if you use the <link
            linkend="command-index-pgp-list-trusted-keys">pgp list trusted
            keys</link> command (you can of course remove it via the <link
            linkend="command-index-pgp-untrust">pgp untrust</link> command as
            well). All of the keys you trust are stored in
            <code>~/.spring_roo_pgp.bpg</code>, which is a binary encoded PGP
            key store which you can also view and manage using normal PGP
            tools. An example of the command to trust a key is shown
            below:<programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">pgp trust</emphasis> --keyId 0xC3A61B10</programlisting></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Alternately, you can decide to simply switch off key
            verification and automatically trust any keys encountered. Such
            keys are stored in your <code>~/.spring_roo_pgp.bpg</code> file.
            You should use caution with this command, although it can be
            convenient if you'd simply like to install some new add-ons and
            their dependencies without considering every key used to sign
            them. To use automatic trust, simply type <link
            linkend="command-index-pgp-automatic-trust">pgp automatic
            trust</link> and press enter:<programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis
                  role="bold">pgp automatic trust</emphasis>
Automatic PGP key trusting enabled (this is potentially unsafe); 
disable by typing 'pgp automatic trust' again</programlisting></para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>Once one of the above have been completed, you can repeat the
        command that attempted to download a <code>httppgp://</code> resource
        and it should succeed.</para>
      </sidebar></para>

    <para>It is easy to extend the capabilities of Spring Roo with installable
    add-ons. This section will offer a basic overview of Roo's add-on
    distribution model and explain how to install new add-ons. If you're
    considering writing an add-on, please refer to the more advanced
    information in <link linkend="internals">Part III</link> of this reference
    guide.</para>

    <para>First of all, it's important to recognize that Roo ships with a
    large number of base add-ons. These built-in add-ons may be all you ever
    require. Nevertheless, there is a growing community of add-ons written by
    people outside the core Roo team. Because the core Roo team do not write
    these add-ons, we've needed to implement an infrastructure so that
    external people can share their add-ons and make it easy for you to
    install them.</para>

    <para>Roo's add-on distribution system encourages individual add-on
    developers to host their add-on web site (we don't believe in a central
    model where we must host add-ons on our servers). The main requirement an
    add-on developer needs to fulfill is their add-ons must be in OSGi format
    and their web site must include an OSGi Bundle Repository (OBR) index
    file. While Roo internally uses OSGi and all modules are managed as OSGi
    bundles, this is transparent and you do not need any familiarity with OSGi
    or bundles to work with the Roo add-on installation system. An OBR file is
    usually named <code>repository.xml</code> and it is available over HTTP.
    If you're curious what these OBR files look like, you can view the Spring
    Roo OBR repository at <link
    xlink:href="http://spring-roo-repository.springsource.org/repository.xml">http://spring-roo-repository.springsource.org/repository.xml</link>.
    Within an OBR file each available Roo-related add-on is listed, along with
    the URL where it is published. The URLs look similar to normal URLs,
    except they will usually specify a <code>httppgp://</code> protocol scheme
    (instead of the more common <code>http://</code>).</para>

    <para>The <code>httppgp://</code> protocol scheme is how we achieve a
    level of security with add-ons. Obviously with every add-on developer able
    to host add-ons on any web site they nominate, it would be difficult for
    you to know whether a particular add-on can be trusted. You probably only
    want to trust add-ons from people you already trust or have cause to
    trust. To this end Roo offers automatic PGP-related signature capabilities
    for any URL that uses the <code>httppgp://</code> scheme. Most Roo add-ons
    use this scheme. The internal step-by-step process that takes place is Roo
    essentially downloads the URL + ".asc" over HTTP. This file is a standard
    PGP detached signature file. PGP detached signature files are increasingly
    common, with most Maven Central artifacts now also offering a signature
    file. If the user's Roo installation trusts the key ID that signed the PGP
    detached signature, Roo will proceed to download the URL. If the user's
    Roo installation does not trust the key ID, an error will be displayed and
    the download will fail (and in turn the add-on installation process will
    fail if the bundle was specified as a <code>httppgp://</code> URL). Please
    see the side-bar for details on how you can trust different key IDs and
    use the PGP-related commands in Roo.</para>

    <para>Completing the picture of Roo's add-on distribution infrastructure
    is RooBot. This is a VMware-hosted service that essentially indexes the
    important content in all public Roo OBR files. RooBot ensures that add-ons
    it indexes are only available over <code>httppgp://</code>, reflecting the
    security model above. Add-on developers can be added into RooBot's index
    in just a couple of minutes via an automated process. Every time Roo
    loads, it automatically downloads the latest RooBot index file. This is
    how it knows which public add-ons are available.</para>

    <para>Enough with the theory, let's move on to the fun piece. In Spring
    Roo you simply use the shell to locate new add-ons. To review the list of
    known add-ons you can use the <link
    linkend="command-index-addon-list">addon list</link> or <link
    linkend="command-index-addon-search">addon search</link> command. This
    lists all add-ons that are in the RooBot-maintained index mentioned
    above:</para>

    <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">addon search</emphasis>
1234 found, sorted by rank; T = trusted developer; R = Roo 1.1 compatible
ID T R DESCRIPTION -------------------------------------------------------------
01 Y Y 2.3.0.0001 This bundle wraps the standard Maven artifact:
       protobuf-java-2.3.0-lite.
02 Y - 0.3.0.RELEASE Addon for Spring Roo to provide generic DAO and query
       methods based on Hades.
03 Y Y 0.9.94.0001 This bundle wraps the standard Maven artifact:
       jline-0.9.94.S2-A (S2-A is a private patched version; see ROO-350 for...
04 - - 1.1.6 Addons that adds Content Negotiating View Resolver configuration
       to your application context: MVC multiple representations By default...
...(output truncated for reference guide inclusion)...
[HINT] use 'addon info id --searchResultId ..' to see details about a search result
[HINT] use 'addon install id --searchResultId ..' to install a specific search result, or
[HINT] use 'addon install bundle --bundleSymbolicName TAB' to install a specific add-on version</programlisting>There
    are various options you can pass to the search command to see more lines
    per result, perform filtering and so on. Just use --TAB as usual to see
    these options.</para>

    <para>If you can't see the add-on you're looking for, you can repeat the
    command with the optional <code>--refresh </code>option. This will refresh
    your local RooBot index from our server.</para>

    <para>To review details about a specific add-on, use the <link
    linkend="command-index-addon-info-id">addon info id</link> command as
    mentioned in the hint at the bottom of the search results. There is also a
    related command called <link
    linkend="command-index-addon-info-bundle">addon info bundle</link> which
    requires a "bundle symbolic name", which is usually the add-on's top-level
    package. However, it's often more convenient to use the search result "ID"
    number (to the left hand side of each row) rather than typing out a bundle
    symbolic name. Let's try this. To view details about the second add-on
    listed, enter this command:</para>

    <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">addon info id </emphasis>--searchResultId 02</programlisting>An
    example of the output of <link linkend="command-index-addon-info-id">addon
    info id</link> is shown below:</para>

    <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">addon info id</emphasis> --searchResultId 02
Name.........: Hades - Roo addon
BSN..........: org.synyx.hades.roo.addon
Version......: 0.3.0.RELEASE
Roo Version..: 1.1.0
Ranking......: 1.0
JAR Size.....: 20458 bytes
PGP Signature: 0xF2C57936 signed by Oliver Gierke (info@olivergierke.de)
OBR URL......: http://hades.synyx.org/static/roo/repo/repository.xml
JAR URL......: httppgp://hades.synyx.org/static/roo/repo/org/synyx/hades/org.syn
               yx.hades.roo.addon/0.3.0.RELEASE/org.synyx.hades.roo.addon-0.3.0.
               RELEASE.jar
Commands.....: 'hades install' [Installs Hades for the project]
Commands.....: 'hades repository' [Creates a Hades repository interface]
Description..: Addon for Spring Roo to provide generic DAO and query methods
               based on Hades.
Comment 1....: Rating [GOOD], Date [17/12/10], Comment [Nice add-on for those
               who want to use a separate repository layer, can be improved in
               functionality]
</programlisting>In the above output "BSN" means bundle symbolic name, which
    is the alternate way of referring to a given add-on. The output also shows
    you the Roo shell commands that are available via the add-on. These
    commands are automatically seen by the Roo shell, so if you typed in this
    case "hades install" without first having installed the add-on, Roo would
    have performed a search and shown you this add-on offered the command.
    This is a great feature and means you can often just type commands you
    think you might need and find out which add-ons offer them without
    performing an explicit search. A similar feature exists for JDBC
    resolution if you try to reverse engineer a database for which there is no
    installed JDBC driver (Roo will automatically suggest the add-on you need
    and instruct you which command to use to install it).</para>

    <para>If you decide to install a specific add-on, simply use the <link
    linkend="command-index-addon-install-id">addon install id</link>
    command:</para>

    <para><programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">addon install id</emphasis> --searchResultId 02
Successfully installed add-on: org.synyx.hades.roo.addon
[Hint] Please consider rating this add-on with the following command:
[Hint] addon feedback bundle --bundleSymbolicName org.synyx.hades.roo.addon --rating ... --comment "..."</programlisting></para>

    <para>If the add-on installation is aborted with a warning that the add-on
    author is currently not trusted, please review the sidebar about modifying
    PGP trusts. To simplify identifying add-ons from developers you already
    trust, the <link linkend="command-index-addon-search">addon search</link>
    results include a "T" column which means "trusted developer". If you see a
    "Y" in that column, you've already trusted that developer's PGP key and
    thus installation will work without needing to add their key. If you see a
    "-" in that column, you'll need to first tell Roo you trust their key (as
    explained in the PGP sidebar).</para>

    <para>As per the [HINT] messages that appear immediately after installing
    an add-on, we appreciate your feedback about the add-ons you use. You can
    use the <link linkend="command-index-addon-feedback-bundle">addon feedback
    bundle</link> command for this purpose, as shown in the console text
    above. If you provide a rating or comment, it will show up for other
    people to see when they use the <link
    linkend="command-index-addon-info-id">addon info</link> command.</para>

    <para>It is generally recommended to restart Roo to ensure the add-on is
    properly initialized. This theoretically isn't necessary in most cases,
    but it doesn't hurt.</para>

    <para>You can also upgrade your existing add-ons by using the addon
    upgrade commands. To do this you should first run the <link
    linkend="command-index-addon-upgrade-settings">addon upgrade
    settings</link> command which allows you to define the desired stability
    level which is taken into account when performing the <link
    linkend="command-index-addon-upgrade-all">addon upgrade all</link>
    command:<programlisting>roo&gt; addon upgrade settings --addonStabilityLevel ANY|MILESTONE|<emphasis
          role="bold">RELEASE</emphasis>|RELEASE_CANDIDATE</programlisting></para>

    <para>If you don't define a stability level through the addon upgrade
    settings command it defaults to RELEASE - meaning only release versions
    will be upgraded (if upgrades for this level are available). Other
    stability levels to choose from are RELEASE_CANDIDATE, MILESTONE, and ANY
    (ie snapshots).</para>

    <para>To list all available upgrades for currently installed add-ons you
    can use the <link linkend="command-index-addon-upgrade-available">addon
    upgrade available</link> command. This will provide an overview of add-ons
    which can be upgraded and their respective stability levels. Furthermore,
    you can also upgrade individual add-ons by using the <link
    linkend="command-index-addon-upgrade-bundle">addon upgrade bundle</link>
    command which allows you to specify the add-on bundle symbolic name (and
    the add-on version in case multiple versions are available). Finally, you
    can use the <link linkend="command-index-addon-upgrade-id">addon upgrade
    id</link> command to upgrade a specific add-on which has appeared in a
    search result to the latest version available.</para>

    <para>Of course, you can remove add-ons as well. To uninstall any given
    add-on, just use the <link linkend="command-index-addon-remove">addon
    remove</link> command. On this occasion we'll use the bundle symbolic name
    (which is available via TAB completion as is usual with
    Roo):<programlisting>roo&gt; <emphasis role="bold">addon remove</emphasis> --bundleSymbolicName de.saxsys.roo.equals.addon
Successfully removed add-on: de.saxsys.roo.equals.addon</programlisting></para>

    <para>Note that all of the "addon" commands only work with add-ons listed
    in the central RooBot index file. This is fine, as most public Roo add-ons
    are listed there. However, sometimes an add-on cannot be published into
    the RooBot index file. The most common reason is that it's an add-on
    internal to your organization, or perhaps it's simply not ready for public
    consumption.</para>

    <para>Even if an add-on is not listed in RooBot, you can still install it.
    The "<link linkend="command-index-osgi-obr-url-add">osgi obr url
    add</link>" command can be used to add the add-on's OBR URL to your Roo
    installation. This command is typically followed by an "<link
    linkend="command-index-osgi-obr-start">osgi obr start</link>" command to
    download and start the add-on. Importantly, the additional security
    verifications performed by RooBot are skipped given RooBot is not used
    with these commands (or other related commands such as <link
    linkend="command-index-osgi-start">osgi start</link>). That means bundles
    you start using the "osgi obr start" command may not use
    <code>httppgp://</code> for PGP signature verification. As such you should
    exercise caution when using any installation-related commands that do not
    start with "addon", as such commands do not use resources subject to the
    RooBot security verifications. Noneless there remain legitimate use cases
    for such distribution styles, so it's good to know Roo supports them as
    well as the more common, user-friendly and more secure "addon"
    commands.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
